<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The differences of the churches of the seperation [sic] contayning a description of the leitourgie and ministerie of the visible church, annexed as a correction and supplement to a litle [sic] treatise lately published, bearing title, Principles and inferences, concerning the visible Church / published ... by Iohn Smyth.</title>
            <author>Smyth, John, d. 1612.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 123 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12553</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22876</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S4092</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">34386992</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 34386992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29151</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12553)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29151)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1905:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The differences of the churches of the seperation [sic] contayning a description of the leitourgie and ministerie of the visible church, annexed as a correction and supplement to a litle [sic] treatise lately published, bearing title, Principles and inferences, concerning the visible Church / published ... by Iohn Smyth.</title>
                  <author>Smyth, John, d. 1612.</author>
                  <author>Smyth, John, d. 1612. Principles and inferences concerning the visible Church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 22 [i.e. 32], [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Publisher and place of publication from STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Error in paging: p. 32 mis-numbered 22.</note>
                  <note>Verso of t.p. contains coat of arms with inscription: Collegium Sancti Johannis Evangelis[tae?] in Academia Cantabrigiensi.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: faded, stained, tightly bound, and with broken type.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: St. John's College (University of Cmabridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Smyth, John, d. 1612. --  Principles and inferences concerning the visible Church.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Controversial literature --  Baptist authors.</term>
               <term>Principles and inferences concerning the visible Church.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Doctrines.</term>
               <term>Baptists --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29151:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29151:1"/>
            <p>THE DIFFERENCES OF THE Churches of the ſeperation:</p>
            <p>Contayning, A DESCRIPTION OF THE LEITOVRGIE AND Miniſterie of the viſible Church:</p>
            <p>Annexed: AS A CORRECTION AND SVPPLEMENT TO A LITLE treatiſe lately publiſhed, bearing title: Principles and inferences, concerning the viſible Church.</p>
            <p>Publiſhed,
<list>
                  <item>1. For the ſatisfaction of every true lover of the truth eſpecially the Brethren of the Seperation that are doubtfull.</item>
                  <item>2. As alſo for the removing of an Vnjuſt calumnie caſt vppon the Brethren of the Seperation of the ſecond English Church at Amſterdam.</item>
                  <item>3. Finally for the cleering of the truth: &amp; the discovering of the myſterie of iniquitie yet further in the worship &amp; offices of the Church.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Divided into two parts
<list>
                  <item>1. Concerning the Leitourgie of the Church</item>
                  <item>2. Concerning the Miniſterie of the Church:</item>
               </list> which hath two ſections</p>
            <p>One of the Elderſhip: Another of the Deacons office wherto aperteineth the Treaſury</p>
            <p>BY IOHN SMYTH</p>
            <q>
               <p>Search the Scriptures:</p>
               <bibl>Ioh. 5.39.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Try all things keep the good thing.</p>
               <bibl>1. Theſ. 5.21.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Beloved: Beleeve not every Spirit.</p>
               <bibl>1. Ioh. 4.1.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>The Spirits of the Prophetts are ſubordinate to the Prophets.</p>
               <bibl>1. Cor. 14.32. 1608.</bibl>
            </q>
            <pb facs="tcp:29151:2"/>
            <figure>
               <head>Collegium Sancti Johannis Evangeliſtae in Academia Cantabrigienſi</head>
               <figDesc>Cambridge bookplate</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:29151:2"/>
            <head>To every true lover of the truth eſpecially to the Brethren of the ſeperation: Salutations.</head>
            <p>NOt long ſince I publiſhed a litle methode intituled principles &amp; inferences concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the viſible Church: Wherin chiefly I purpoſed to manifeſt the true conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church, a matter of abſolute neceſſitie &amp; now ſo cleered by the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the late witneſſes of Ieſus Chriſt the auncient brethren of the ſeperation as that it ſeemeth nothing can further be added, The abſolute necesſitie of the true conſtitution appeareth, becauſe if the Church be truly conſtituted &amp; framed, ther is a true Church: the true ſpowſe of Chriſt: if the Church be falſely conſtituted, ther is a falſe Church: &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he is not the true ſpowſe ef Chriſt: Herein therfor eſpecially are thoſe auncient bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren to be honoured, that they have reduced the Church to the true Primitive &amp; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolique conſtitution which conſiſteth in theſe three things. 1. The true matter which are ſayntes only. 2. The true forme which is the vniting of them together in the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. 3. The true propertie which is communion in all the holy things, &amp; the powre of the L. Ieſus Chriſt, for the maintayning of that communion. To this bleſſed work of the L. wherin thoſe auncient brethten have labored I know not what may more be added: I thincke rather ther can nothing be added: but now Antichriſt is perfectly both diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered &amp; conſumed in reſpect of the conſtitution by the evidence of the truth, which is the brightnes of Chriſts comming. Now al though they have alſo verie worthelie em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed them ſelves in the Leitourgie, Miniſterie, &amp; Treaſurie of the Church, both in diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering the forgeries &amp; corruptions which the man of ſyune had intermingled, &amp; alſo in ſome good degree reducing them to ther primitive puritie wherin they weere by the Apoſtles left vnto the Churches: Yet wee are perſwaded that herein Antichriſt is not vtterlie eythet revealed or aboliſhed, but that in a verie high degree he is exalted even in the true conſtituted Churches: In regard wherof, as alſo being enforced vppon ſome courgie &amp; miniſtrie of the Church: The Miniſterie I ſay conſiſting of the Preſbytery &amp; Deacons office, wherto apertyneth the Treaſurie, &amp; that for theſe ends: partly that the truth wee walk in may be manifeſted to the world, among whome our opinion and practiſe is ſo ſtraungely &amp; falſely traduced: partly that the differences betwixt vs &amp; the auncienter brethren of the ſeperation may appeare, &amp; therby men may be occaſioned to trye the truth from error &amp; to hold it faſt. And although in this writing ſomthing ther is which overtwharteth my former judgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in ſome treatiſes by mee formerly publiſhed: Yet I would intreat the teader not to impute that as a fault vnto mee: rather it ſhould be accounted a vertue to retract erroers: Know therfor that latter thoughs oft tymes are better then the former: &amp; I do profeſſe this (that no man account it ſtraunge), that <hi>I</hi> will every day as my erroers ſhalbe d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcovered confeſſe them &amp; renounce them: For it is our covenant made with our God to forſake every evill way whither in opinion or practiſe that ſhalbe manifeſted vnto vs at any tyme: &amp; therfor lett no man plead now, as ſome have formerly done, theſe men are inconſtant: they would have they know not what: They will never be ſatisfied &amp; the like: For wee profeſſe even ſo much as they object: That wee are inconſtant in erroer: that wee would have the truth, though in many particulars wee are ignorant of it: Wee will never be ſatiſfied in endevoring to
<pb facs="tcp:29151:3"/>reduce the worſhip and miniſtery of the Church, to the primitive Apoſtolique inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from which as yet it is ſo farr diſtant: VVherfor my earneſt deſire is, that my laſt writing may be taken as my preſent judgment &amp; ſo farre forth as it overthwarteth any former writing of myne let it be accounted a voluntary retractation &amp; vnſeyned repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tance of my former errors &amp; evil wayes before the whole earth. And lett no man bee of<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fended at vs for that wee differ from the auncient brethren of the ſeperation in the Leitourgie Preſbyterie &amp; Treaſurie of the Church: for wee hold not our ſayth at any mans pleaſure or in reſpect of perſons, neyther doe wee bynd our ſelves to walk accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to other mens lynes further then they walk in the truth: neyther lett the world think that wee approve them in all their practiſes: let them juſtifie their proceedinges or repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of them: wee have (wee willingly &amp; thankfully acknowledge) receaved much light of truth from their writinges for which mercy we alwayes bleſſe our God: &amp; for which help wee alwayes ſhall honour them in the Lord and in the truth. But as Paull withſtood Peter to his face &amp; ſeperated from Barnabas that good man that was full of the holy ghoſt &amp; of fayth, for juſt cauſſes: So muſt they give vs leave to love the truth &amp; honour the Lord more then any man or Church vppon earth. Now if any of the adverſaries of vs both ſhall heerby take occaſion of offence, thereby to ſpeake evill, or to withold or revolt from the truth: let theſe men conſider with themſelves: Firſt: that they even in that theyr Aegyptian da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kneſſe wherein they walk have their moſt violent oppoſitions &amp; deadly contentions: Agayne, the Apoſtle hath foretold that it is neceſſary their ſhould bee diſſentions even in the true Churches that they which are approved may bee knowne: beſides the truth ſhall by our differences bee further clee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, &amp; theyr Antichriſtian worſhip &amp; Miniſtery more &amp; more detected, &amp; caſt into the bottomleſſe pitt from whence it iſſued. Finally the Apoſtle ſaith that Chriſt is a ſtone to ſtumble at &amp; a rock of offence to the diſobedient aſwell as a cheef corner ſtone elect &amp; pretious to them that beleeve: &amp; bleſſed are they that are not offended at Chriſt or his truth. So deſyring the reader to weygh well what I plead &amp; not to bee offended at the manifold quotations which are of neceſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ty that by places compared together the truth which is a myſtery may appeare &amp; Antichriſtianiſme which is the myſtery of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty may bee diſcovered, I ceaſe, commending him to the grace of God in Ieſus Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſt, who in due tyme will bring his people out of Aegypt &amp; Babylon ſpiritually ſo called, though for a ſeaſon they are there kept in Antichriſtian captivity &amp; g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eevous ſpirituall ſlavery: which the Lord in his due tyme effect, Amen, Amen.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Iohn Smyth.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:29151:3"/>
            <list>
               <head>The principall contents of this treatise &amp; our differences from the auncyent brethren of the Seperation.</head>
               <item>1 Wee hould that the worſhip of the new teſtament properly ſo called is ſpirituall pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceeding originally from the hart: &amp; that reading out of a booke (though a lawfu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l ecle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iaſtical action) is no part of ſpirituall worſhip, but rather the invention of the man of ſynne it beeing ſubſtituted for a part of ſpirituall worſhip.</item>
               <item>2 Wee hould that seeing propheſiing is a parte of spirituall worship: therefore in time of propheſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yng it is vnlawfull to have the booke as a helpe before the eye</item>
               <item>3 wee hould that ſeeing singinging a psalme is a parte of spirituall worship therefore it is vnlawfull to have the booke before the eye in time of ſinginge a psalme</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> wee hould that the Presbytery of the church is vniforme: &amp; that the triformed Pres<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>byterie consiſting of three kinds of Elders viz. Paſtors Teachers Rulers is none o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Gods Ordinance but mans devise.</item>
               <item>5 wee hold that all the Elders of the Church are Paſtors: and that lay Elders (to called) are Antichriſtian.</item>
               <item>6 wee hold that in contributing to the Church Treaturie their ought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bee both a se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>paration from them that are without &amp; a sanctification of the whole action by Prayer &amp; Thankesgiving.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:29151:4"/>
            <head>THE DIFFERENCES OF THE CHVRCHES OF THE SEPE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, Conteyning a deſcription of the Leitourgie &amp; Miniſterie of the viſible Church Annexed as a correction &amp; ſupplement to a litle treatiſe lately publiſhed bearing title principles, &amp; inferences concerning the viſible Church.</head>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>THE FIRST PART. concerning the Leitourgie of the Church</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>Cap. 1. of the Kingdom of the Saynts.</head>
                  <p>The viſible Church by the Apoſtle is called a Kingly preiſthood. 1. pet. 2.9. and the Saynts are Kings &amp; Preiſts vnto God. Revel. 1.6.</p>
                  <p>The Saynts as Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ule the viſible Church. 1. Cor. 5.12. pſal. 149.9. Mat. 18.15-17. 1. Cor. 6.1.-9.</p>
                  <p>The viſible Church is Chriſts Kingdom. Mat. 8.12. Ioh. 18.33-37. Act. 1.3, 1. Cor. 15.24.25. Hebr. 12.28.</p>
                  <p>The members of the viſible Church are called the children of the Kingdom. Mat. 8.12. And are vnder the government of the Church: Marc. 13.34, 1. Cor. 6.1.9. &amp; vnder the governme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nt of Chriſt. Luk. 19.27.</p>
                  <p>The actions of the Church in adminiſtring the Kingdom are actions of oppoſition, difference, plea, &amp; ſtrif: as in admonition, examination, excommunication, pacification, abſolution, &amp;c. 1. Cor. 5.3-5. &amp; 6.1-9. &amp; 2. Ep. 2.6.7. Mat. 18-15-17. Revel. 2.2, 2. Chron. 19.10-11.</p>
                  <p>Hethetto aperteyneth conference &amp; diſputation. Luc. 2.46.47. Act. 6.9. &amp; 17: 2, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with pſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l. 122.5. 1. King. 3.16-27.</p>
                  <p>In examination of opinions &amp; facts alſo in conference &amp; diſputation evidences of all ſorts may be produced for finding out of the truth. Revel. 2.2. 1. King. 3.25-27.</p>
                  <p>Evidences are of divers natures: as confesſions &amp; lotts: Ioſh. 7.16-21. Oathes: Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.10.11. bookes of all ſortes. Dan, 9 2-1, King. 14.19. Act. 7.22. &amp; 17.28. 1. Cor. 15.33. Tit. 1.12. Iude. verſ. 14. compared with 1. Timoth. 1.4. &amp; Luk. 3.25-27. namly tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, dictionaries, hiſtories, chronicles, commentaries, &amp;c, all which may for evidence of the truth be brought into the Church by neceſſary conſequence.</p>
                  <p>Actions of adminiſtring the Church or Kingdom are not actions of ſpirituall worſhip properly ſo called, for as the Kingdome and Preiſthood of the old Teſtament were diſtinct as alſo their actions ſeverall: Heb. 7.14. Gen. 49.10. Deut. 33.8-11. 2. Chron. 26.18. pſal. 122 4-5: So are the Kingdom &amp; Preiſthood of the new Teſtament &amp; their actions alſo: which were typed by the other. Heb. 5.4.5. Act. 15.7-29. with 13.2, 3.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 2. of the Preiſthood of the ſaynts.</head>
                  <p>Thus much of the Kingdom: now followeth the Preiſthood of the Church.</p>
                  <p>The ſaynts as Preiſts offer vp ſpirituall ſacrifices acceptable to God by Ieſus Chriſt. 1. pet. 2.5.</p>
                  <p>Spirituall ſacrifices are ſuch as originally proceed from the ſpirit: &amp; they are called ſpirituall in oppoſition to the carnall or literall ſacrifices performed by the ſacrificing Preiſts of the old Teſtament: which originally proceeded from the lettre: by proportion alſo ſee, Ioh. 1.17, 2. Cor. 3.6. Gal. 3.5. Ioh. 4.20-24.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:29151:4"/>
                  <p>The actions of the Church in diſpencing the preiſthood are actions of concord or v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: Act. 4.24-32. philip. 3.16. Epheſ. 4.3-6.</p>
                  <p>Actions of the Preiſthood of the ſaynts are actions of ſpirituall worſhip properly ſo called. Deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 33.10. 1. pet. 2.5. compared with Revel. 8.3. Heb. 13.10. philip. 2.17. Act. 13.2, 1. Cor. 11.4. &amp; 14.15.22.26-31.</p>
                  <p>In the worſhip of God properly ſo called the ſaynts are not to oppoſe, contradict, examine, or cenſure: to propound doubtfull &amp; controverſall points of doctryne: but in vnion ſpirituall to offer vp one &amp; the ſame ſpirituall ſacryfice to the Lord. Act. 4.24-32. 1. Cor. 11.18-20. &amp; 10.16.17.</p>
                  <p>If any thing doubtfull or falſe be delivered in tyme of ſpirituall worſhip it is to be examyned &amp; cenſured afterward. 1. Cor. 14.31-33.40. compared with Revel. 2.2. Act. 17.11.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 3. of Spirituall worſhip &amp; of the Spirit.</head>
                  <p>Concerning ſpirituall worſhip conſider theſe things following.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The Fountayne from whence it proceedeth.</item>
                     <item>2. The helpes wherby it is ſupported or furthered,</item>
                     <item>3. The eſſence or nature wherin properly it couſiſteth.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>The Fountayne from whence ſpirituall worſhip proceedeth is the ſpirit. Act. 1.4.5. &amp; 2.4.17.18, 1. Cor. 12.4, 7.11. Eph. 5.18.19.</p>
                  <p>The ſpirit ſignifieth 2. things. 1. the ſpirit of God. 2. the ſpirit of man: that is the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate part of the ſoule. Act. 2.17.18, 1. Cor. 12.4. Rom. 7.6. Galath. 3.2.3.</p>
                  <p>The Regenerate part of the ſoule is eyther the ſanctified memory, the ſanctified judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the ſanctified hart &amp; affections, the ſanctified conſcience: from all theſe muſt ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall worſhip proceed. Pſal. 103.1. 2. Mat. 22 37, 1. Timoth. 1.5.</p>
                  <p>The work of the holy ſpirit is to ſuggeſt matter &amp; to move the regenerate part of the ſoule, 1. Cor. 12.8-11, Ioh. 14.26, Luk. 24.32-45.</p>
                  <p>The work of the memory is to have in a readyneſſe ſufficiency of fit matter for the ſpirituall worſhip, pſal. 103.2, &amp; 119.16.93.</p>
                  <p>The work of the judgment or vnderſtanding is to diſcerne &amp; judge truth from falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, right from wrong, good from bad, fit from vnſit, 1. Cor. 14.29-32, &amp; 11.29, Coloſ. 1.9. &amp; 3.16, Philip. 1.9.10.</p>
                  <p>The work of the hart &amp; affections is to be moved according to the qualitie of the matter &amp; kind of the worſhip. Iam. 5.13, Ezra. 3.10-13, 1. Cor. 14.24.25.</p>
                  <p>The work of the conſcience is a ſorowfull or confortable teſtimony anſwerable to the matter handled, 1. Timoth. 1.5. Act. 23.1.</p>
                  <p>Finally the work of the Regenerat part of the ſoule is an Eccho correſpondent to the work of the holy Spirit &amp; the condition of the word of God which in tyme of ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uall worſhip is adminiſtred. pſal. 27.8. Eſay. 66.5. Mat. 13.9. Heb. 10.5-7. Caut. 5.4.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 4. of quenching the Spirit.</head>
                  <p>In performing ſpirituall worſhip wee muſt take heed of quenching the ſpirit. 1. Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.19. 1. Cor. 14.30. Iob 32.18-20.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29151:5"/>
                  <p>The Spirit is quenched two wayes: By ſilence. By ſet formes of worſhip. Pſal. 40.1-3. 1. Cor. 14.29-32. compared with. 1 Theſ. 5.19.20.</p>
                  <p>The Spirit is quenched by ſilence when fit matter is revealed to one that ſitteth by &amp; he wthholdeth it in tyme of prophecying:</p>
                  <p>The Spirit is quenched by ſett formes of worſhip, for therein the ſpirit is not at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to vtter it ſelf, but is bounded in: contrary to. Act. 2.4. &amp; 2. Cor. 3.17. compared with Ioh. 4.24. &amp; Gal. 4.31. &amp;. 5.1.</p>
                  <p>Sett formes of worſhip are eyther in the memory, or in the book.</p>
                  <p>Saying ſet formes, of worſhip by rote is quenching the Spirit: &amp; Reading ſett formes of worſhip out of a book is quenching the Spirit: for in the one the Spirit is not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted but the ſtrength of the memory, in the other the matter is not brought out of the ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>, but out of the book: &amp; ſo in neyther of them the Spirit is at liberty.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 5. of the helps of Spiritual worſhip.</head>
                  <p>Thus much concerning the Fountayne from whence Spiritual worſhip commeth: now follow the helps wherby Spiritual worſhip is furthered or ſupported.</p>
                  <p>The helps are eyther inward or outward.</p>
                  <p>The inward helps are only the word &amp; the ſpirit. Eph. 5.18.19. Col. 3.16. Rom. 8.26.</p>
                  <p>The outward helps are the manifeſtation of the Spirit: &amp; the ſeales of the covenant: 1. Cor. 12.7. &amp; 2.4. &amp; Act. 2.4.42. with the inſtruments creatures &amp; actions appertey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning therto.</p>
                  <p>Inſtruments: as the tong &amp; eare, to ſpeake, heate &amp; taſt withal: Act. 2.4.8. 1. cor. 11.24.</p>
                  <p>Creatures as bread, wine, water: Act. 8.36-39. 1. Cor. 11.23. Mat. 26.27-29.</p>
                  <p>Actions as ſpeaking, hearing, breaking bread, powring out wine, eating, drincking, waſhing with water, by conſequent from the former places.</p>
                  <p>The publiſhing of the covenant of grace &amp; the putting to of the ſeales is only one concrete action or part of worſhip, for the publiſhing of the covenant giveth being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o the ſeales, otherwiſe breaking bread &amp; baptiſing are but putting of ſeales to a blanck.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 6. concerning bookes &amp; writing.</head>
                  <p>Here a queſtion is to be diſcuſſed: wither a book be a lawful help to further vs in tyme of ſpiritual worſhip. Revel. 10.10.11. Ezech. 3.3.4.</p>
                  <p>Bookes or writings are ſignes or pictures of things ſignified therby.</p>
                  <p>Writings are to be conſidered in the concrete or in the abſtract.</p>
                  <p>In the concrete writings import both the ſigne &amp; the thing ſignified therby, that is both the characters &amp; the matter.</p>
                  <p>In the abſtract writings import the ſigne in relation to the thing ſignified therby: vis: lettres, ſillables, wordes, ſyntaxe.</p>
                  <p>Every writing is compounded of wordes.</p>
                  <p>Every worde is made of lettres &amp; ſillables except that ſome lettres &amp; ſillables are wordes.</p>
                  <p>Lettres or characters are ſignificative. Revel. 1.8, &amp; 13.18. Alpha, Omega, Chi. Xi, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29151:5"/>ſignify, firſt, laſt, 600, 60, 6.</p>
                  <p>Wordes are ſignificative in the firſt or ſecond intention: as Amen in the firſt intention ſig<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nifieth truth or truly. Mat. 5.18. Amen in the ſecond intention ſignifieth Chriſt Revel. 3.14. So doth Logos ſignify alſo and many other wordes of Scripture.</p>
                  <p>Syntaxe or joyning of wordes in order ſignifieth diſcourſe,</p>
                  <p>As ſingle wordes ſignify Logicall relations or arguments. So Syntaxe or wordes com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pounded in ſentence ſignifieth Axiomes, Syllogiſmes, Methode.</p>
                  <p>Therefore wordes and ſyntaxe are ſignes of thinges, and of the relations and reaſon of thinges</p>
                  <p>Hence it followeth that bookes or writinges are in the nature of picturer or Images &amp; therefore in the nature of ceremonies: &amp; ſo by conſequent reading a booke is cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>moniall. For as the Beaſt in the Sacrifices of the ould Teſtament was ceremoniall ſo was the killing of the Beaſt ceremoniall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 7. Of the kindes of bookes or writinges.</head>
                  <p>Thus much of the nature of bookes or writinges: Now follow the kindes of bookes or the diſtribution of writinges.</p>
                  <p>writinges may bee diſtinguiſhed according to the ſubject or efficient.</p>
                  <p>The ſubject of writinges are paper, parchment, wood, ſtone, metall. &amp;c</p>
                  <p>If writinges bee in paper or parchment they bee called bookes, as may bee gathered from. Deut. 31.24-26. Ierem 36.4.</p>
                  <p>If writinges be ingraven in ſtone wood or metal it is caled graving or carving: Exo. 28.11. 2. Cor. 3.7. Ioſh. 8.32.</p>
                  <p>The efficient of writinges are two: God, or Man.</p>
                  <p>God himſelfe firſt engraved the law in tables of ſtone. Exod. 31.18.</p>
                  <p>Men are of two ſortes: Inſpired, or ordinary men.</p>
                  <p>Men Inſpired by the Holy Ghoſt are the Holy Prophets &amp; Apoſtles who wrote the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ſcriptures by inſpiration. 2. Pet. 1.21. 2 Tim. 3.16. Rom. 1.2. namely the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brue of the ould teſtament &amp; the greeke of the new Teſtament.</p>
                  <p>The Holy Scriptures viz. the Originalls Hebrew &amp; Greek are given by Divine inſpira<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion &amp; in their firſt donation were without error moſt perfect &amp; therefore Canonicall.</p>
                  <p>Ordinary men write bookes of divers kindes among the reſt ſuch as have the word of God or Holy Scriptures for their object are called Theological writinges: among them Tranſlations of the Holy Scriptures into the mother tong are cheifly to be eſteemed, as beeing the moſt principall, yet only as the ſtreame iſsuing from the fountayne, or as the greateſt river of the mayne ſea.</p>
                  <p>No writinges of ordinary men how holy or good ſoever are given by inſpiration, &amp; therefore are ſubject to error &amp; imperfect &amp; ſo Apocrypha.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 8. Of the Originalls or Holy Scriptures, &amp; of the partes of Holy Scripture.</head>
                  <p>Holy Scriptures (as all other writinges whatſoever,) conſiſt of two partes: of the tong &amp; character &amp; of the ſubſtance or matter ſignified by the character.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:29151:6"/>
                  <p>The tong or character hath apertaining to it the grammar and the Rhethorick wher of the tong or character is the ſubiect.</p>
                  <p>The matter or ſubſtance of the ſcripture hath in it, Logick, Hiſtory, Cronology, Coſ mography, Genealogy, Philoſophy, Theologie and other like matter.</p>
                  <p>The principall parte of the matter is the Theologie</p>
                  <p>A Translation of the holy originalls may expreſse very much of the matter contayned in or ſignified by the originall characters: it can expreſse alſo much of the Rhetho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rickas Tropes &amp; Figures of ſentence.</p>
                  <p>No Translation can poſsibly expreſse all the matter of the holy originalls, nor a thou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſand thinges in the Grammar, Rhethorick, &amp; characte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of the tong.</p>
                  <p>A Translation ſo far forth as it doth truly &amp; fully expreſse any thing of the originals may be ſaide inſpired of God &amp; no further.</p>
                  <p>Hence it followeth that a tranſlation be it never ſo good is mixt with mens deviſes, imperfect, not equipollent to the originalles in a thouſand particulars.</p>
                  <p>The holy originalles ſignifie and repreſent to our eyes heavenly things therfor the book of the law is called a ſimilitude of an heavenly thing. Heb. 9.19-23.</p>
                  <p>Holy Scriptures or writings beganne with Moſes. Exob. 24.4. &amp; 31.18. Ioh. 1.17. 2. Cor. 3.7.</p>
                  <p>Before Moſes holy men propheſyed out of their harts &amp; receaved &amp; kept the truth of doctryne by tradition from hand to hand: 2. Pet. 2.5. Iude verſ. 14.15. Deut. 31.24.</p>
                  <p>When Moſes had written the lawe, he cauſed it to be put by the arke in the moſt holy place, as a witneſſe againſt the people. deut. 31.26. therfor the Apoſtle calleth it the hand<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>writing in ordinances which was contrary to vs, which Chriſt nayled to his croſſe. Col. 2.14. Eph. 2.15.</p>
                  <p>Hence it followeth that the holy originals the Hebrue ſcriptures of the old teſtament are ceremonyes. 2. Cor. 3.3.7. Nomb. 5.23.24. &amp; by neceſſary conſequent.</p>
                  <p>The book or tables of ſtone typed vnto the Iewes their hard hart voyde of the true vnderſtanding of the lawe. 2. Cor. 3.3. Heb. 8.10. Ezech. 36.26.27. 2. Cor. 3.14.15.</p>
                  <p>The Inck wherewith the lettres were written ſignified the Spirit of God: 2. Cor, 3.3. Heb. 8.10. compared with Exod. 31.18.</p>
                  <p>The lettres written or characters engraven ſignifieth the work of the Spirit, who alone doth write the law in our harts. by proportion: alſo Deut 9.10. compared with Heb. 8.10</p>
                  <p>Reading the words of the law out of the book ſignifieth the vttering of the word of God out of the hart: by proportion. ſee alſo. 2. Cor. 3.2.3.6. 1. Cor. 12.7.</p>
                  <p>The writings of the old Teſtament being ceremonial are therfor abolished by Chriſt only ſo far forth as they are ceremonial: Col. 2.14 20. Gal. 4.9.</p>
                  <p>The thing ſignified by the book viz: the law of God &amp; the new teſtament remayneth 2 Cor. 3: 11.7. Heb. 8.6.7.13.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 9, How the Originalls or Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are to be vſed.</head>
                  <p>The Scriptures of the old Teſtament are commaunded to the Church 2. Pet. 1.19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29151:6"/>&amp;. 2. Timoth. 3.16. as alſo the Scriptures of the new Teſtament: 1. Theſ. 5.27. Col. 4.16. &amp; by proportion.</p>
                  <p>Heer conſider theſe things,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. How the Scriptures are to be vſed: 2. How they are not to be vſed.</p>
                  <p>The Holy Scriptures are the Fountayne of all truth, Ioh. 17.17. compared with 2. Timoth. 3.16.17.</p>
                  <p>They are the ground &amp; foundacion of our fayth, Epheſ. 2.20. compared with Ioh. 5.39. &amp; 17.3.</p>
                  <p>By them all doctrynes &amp; every Spiritt is to be judged: Eſay 8.20. 1. Ioh. 4.1. Act. 17.11.</p>
                  <p>They are to be read in the Church &amp; to be interpeted: Col. 4.16. compared with Luk. 24.27. &amp; 1. Cor. 14, 27. &amp; 12.10. by proportion. 2. Pet. 3.16.</p>
                  <p>Nevertheleſſe the Holy Scriptures are not reteyned as helps before the eye in tyme of Spirituall worship: Reaſons are theſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 10. Reaſons proving the Originals not to be given as helps before the eye in worship.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. Bicauſe Chriſt vſed the book to fulfill all righteouſnes Mat. 3.15. &amp; having by the vſe of the book fulfilled the law of reading he ſhut the book in the Synagogue, to ſignifie that that ceremony of bookworship, or the miniſterie of the lettre was now exſpired, &amp; finished. Luk. 4.20. Ioh, 19.30.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Bicauſe reading wordes out of a book is the miniſtration of the lettre, 2. Cor. 3.6. namely a part of the miniſterie of the old Teſtament which is abolished: Heb. 8.13: 2: cor. 3.11.13. &amp; the miniſtery of the new teſtament is the miniſterie of the ſpirit. 2. Cor. 3.6.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Bicauſe vppon the day of Pentecoſt &amp; many yeeres after the churches of the new teſtament did vſe no bookes in tyme of ſpiritual worship but prayed, propheſyed, &amp; ſang Pſalmes meerely out of their harts. Act. 2.4.42. &amp; 10.44-48. &amp; 19.6. 1. cor. 14.15-17.26.37</p>
                  <p n="4">4. Bicauſe no example of the Scripture can be ſhewed of any man ordinary or extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary that at or after the day of Pentecoſt vſed a book in praying, propheſying &amp; ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ng Pſalmes: if yea: let it be done &amp; wee yeeld.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Bicauſe none of the books of the new Teſtament were written many yeeres after the day of Pentecoſt, at the leaſt ſeaven yeeres: &amp; the Churches all that tyme could not vſe the books of the new Teſtament which they had not:</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Bicauſe the Churches of the Greekes had no bookes to vſe that they might vſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>awfully: for they vnderſtood not Hebrue: &amp; the Septuagints tranſlation ought not to be vſed or made, &amp; the Apoſtles made no Greek tranſlation: And if the Apoſtles read the Hebrue an vnknowne tong in the Greek Churches it could not be a lawfull worship, bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it edified not: if they had the Hebrue before their eyes &amp; interpeted Greek, let it be ſhewed when &amp; where &amp; wee yeeld vnto it.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Bicauſe as in prayer the ſpirit only is our help &amp; ther is no outward help given of God for that kind of worship: So alſo in propheſying &amp; ſinging. 1. Cor. 11.4. &amp; 14.16,</p>
                  <p n="8">8. Bicauſe it is againſt the nature of ſpiritual worship: for when we read wee receave matter from the book into the hart, when we pray propheſy or ſing we utter matter out of the hart vnto the eare of the Church; Ezech, 2.8-19, &amp; 3.1-4. Revel. 10.8-11.</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29151:7"/>
                  <p n="9">9. Bicauſe vpon the day of Pentecoſt fyerie cloven tongs did appeare, not fiery cloven bookes. Ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.3. &amp; alwaies ther muſt be a proportion betwixt the type and the thing typed: vpon the day of Pentecoſt the fiery law was given in bookes Deut: 33.2. Exo: 24.4.12. vpon the day of Pentecoſt the fiery goſpel was given in tonges Act: 2.3. Mat: 3 11. Act: 1.5. the booke therefore was proper for them, the tonge for vs <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> 10. Bicauſe as all the worſhip which Moſes taught began in the letter outwardly, &amp; ſo proceeded inwardly to the ſpirit of the faithfull: ſo contrariwiſe all the worſhip of the new teſtament ſignified by that typicall worſhip of Moſes muſt beginne at the Spirit, &amp; not at the letter originally. 2. Cor: 3.6.8. 1. Cor: 12.7. or els the heavenly thinge is not anſwerable to the ſimilitude thereof:</p>
                  <p>Therfor as in prayer the book is laid aſide, &amp; that by the confeſſion of the auncient brethren of the ſeperation: ſo muſt it be alſo in propheſying &amp; ſinging of Pſalmes as we are perſwaded. 1. Cor. 11.4. &amp; 14.15.16.26.</p>
                  <p>Quere, whither the Prophets of the Church may not in tyme of Spiritual worſhip, take the originals, &amp; interpret out of them a text, &amp; then ſhut the book &amp; propheſy from that ground of holy Scripture ſo interpreted. Luk. 4.16-20.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 11. objections for book worſhip anſwered.</head>
                  <p>The firſt objection.</p>
                  <p>Reading in the old Teſtament was commaunded by Moſes. Deut. 31.9-13. was ampli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by David. 1. Chron. 16. &amp; 25. was practiſed by Ioſiah 2. Chron. 34.30. by Ezra &amp; Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah Nehem. 8.8. &amp; 9.3. allowed by our Savior Chriſt Luk. 4.16. &amp; by the Apoſtles, Act. 13.14.15. &amp;c reported as a thing of auncient approved continuance. Act. 15.21.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the firſt objection.</p>
                  <p>Firſt the reading commaunded by Moſes was only once every ſeaven yeere. Deut. 31.10.11 &amp; therfor it was no part of ordinary worſhip, &amp; ther is no commaundement in Moſes given eyther to the Preiſts or Levites for ordinary reading of the law in the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle.</p>
                  <p>Secondly: Hence it followeth that reading in the old Teſtament was no part of the worſhip of the tabernacle or temple, or of the ſervice performed by the Prieſts therein, for all the worſhip that was appointed by Moſes for the Preiſts was limited to the holy place, whither the people were not admitted.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly: therfor reading was of another nature performed in the vtter court or Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue or els where, eyther by the levites or any other learned men of what tribe ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: Mat. 23.2. Luk. 4.16. Act. 13-15. compared with. Act. 15-21. Deut. 31 9-11.1. Chron. 10.4.7.37.39. &amp; 15.1-8. &amp; 28.13.2. Chron. 34.14.30.31. Nehem. 8. &amp; 9. ſo no part of worſhip properly ſo called, but only a ceremoniall ground or ſoundation, of inward or outward ſpiritual worſhip common to the Churches of all ages.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly: it is not denyed but that reading now is to be vſed in the Church: only we ſay it is not a part of ſpiritual worſhip, or a lawful meanes in tyme of ſpiritual worſhip.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:29151:7"/>
                  <p>The ſecond objection</p>
                  <p>Reading is commaunded in the new teſtament Coloſ: 4.16. 1. Theſ: 5.27. and a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed thereto Revel: 1.3. and the commaundement is that it be practiſed in the church: therefore it is a part or meanes of the worſhip of the new teſtament.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the ſecond objection.</p>
                  <p>Not euerie thinge performed in the church is a parte of ſpirituall worſhip, forall the partes of publique adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Kingdome are done in the church, and yet cannot be ſayd to be partes of ſpirituall worſhip properly ſo called. Chap: 1. and 2.</p>
                  <p>Moreover when he commaundeth his Epiſtles to be read in the Churches, his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is not ſtrictly literall: that is, that the very wordes which he wrote ſhould be repea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted verbatim out of the booke: but his meaning is that the fenſe of the wordes or the meaning of the Apoſtle ſhould be related to the brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whither by reading the very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wordes, by expounding the meaning by interpreting or tranſlating. For if his meaning be that the very wordes he wrote be literaly read: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Greek wordes muſt be repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out of the booke to all nations: which is contrary to. 1. Cor. 14.26. If his meaning be, that the ſenſe ſhould be given any way, by tranſlating, by reading the tranſlation, by interpreting his meaning in a paraphraſe, commentary &amp;c. then how will it follow that reading the Greek tong which is not vnderſtood in the Engliſh Churches is a law full part of ſpirituall worship according to the literall ſignification of readings?</p>
                  <p>Further the Apoſtle wrote his Epiſtles to the Colloſſians, &amp; Theſſalonians &amp; the other Churches vppon particular occaſions for partcular endes, and the commaundement of reading then was ſpeciall in thoſe reſpects to them: and the intent of the Apoſtle is not to enioyne the reading of them every day &amp; in tyme of Spiritual worſhip to al Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: yet wee do acknowledg the abſolute neceſſity of reading &amp; ſearching the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, Ioh. 5.39.</p>
                  <p>Againe that reading is a lawful yea neceſſary meanes or help to further vs to Spiritual worship is not denyed, but this is denyed that it is a lawful help in tyme of worship, or a lawful part of Spiritual worship. For it is confeſſed &amp; defended by the auncient brethre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſeperation, that the originals are no lawful help in tyme of prayer: So ſay we they are no lawful help in tyme of propheſying &amp; ſinging Pſalmes, &amp; that by equal propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for ther is the ſame reaſon of helps in all the parts of Spiritual worship, during the tyme of performing the worship.</p>
                  <p>The third objection.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtle 1. Tim. 4.13-16. commaundeth. Timothie &amp; ſo all Elders to attend to reading wher reading is joyned with exhortation &amp; doctryne &amp; ſo importeth that it is to be vnderſtood of the joyning of reading in tyme of Spiritual worship</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the third objection.</p>
                  <p>The circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtances of the place being <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>el conſidered w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> afoard that Paul ſpeaketh no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:29151:8"/>of the execution of his office, but of preparing himſelf to the execution of his office: which is attayned by reading the Scriptures wherby men are fitted with matter fitt to teach &amp; exhort: for by this meanes the gift o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prophecy was preſerved in Timothie vſ. 14. &amp; by this meanes his proficiency ſhould be manifeſted. vſ. 15. by this meanes he ſhould the better ſave mens ſoules, vſ. 16.</p>
                  <p>The fourth objection.</p>
                  <p>Let it be graunted that the Apoſtles &amp; Evangeliſts vſed no bookes being extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary men &amp; having the extraordinary direction of the ſpirit, for they needed no ſuch helps of bookes as wee doe: Yet wee being men ordinary have need of bookes, therefor they by the direction of the Spirit both have written bookes for our vſe, &amp; have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs to vſe them.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the fourth objection.</p>
                  <p>This objection may aswell fit bringing of bookes into the tyme of prayer, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce they are juſtly baniſhed: for it may be ſayd that the Apoſtles were extraordinary men, &amp; needed no bookes for prayer, but wee need books to help our infirmity: &amp; why may not a man aswel ſay the Apoſtle commaundeth the reading of prayers, &amp; promiſeth a blesſing to reading of prayers in tyme of prayer as otherwiſe.</p>
                  <p>Again, though the holy Spirit be not given to vs in the ſame manner &amp; meaſure as to the Apoſtles, yet we have the ſame Spirit to help vs as they had, &amp; to the ſame ordinary purpoſes, is he ſent to vs by Chriſt as to them: namely to help our infirmityes: Rom. 8. 26. for the work of the miniſtery: Eph. 4.12. to be our annoynting, 1. Ioh. 2.27. to lead in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all truth: Ioh 16.13. to be our paraclete: Ioh. 14.16. &amp; ſo by conſequent to help vs to pray, propheſy, &amp; prayſe God.</p>
                  <p>Againe this objection ſeemeth to eſtabliſh two formes of propheſying, one without bookes by the Apoſtles for many yeeres in the Church: another with bookes afterward taught by the Apoſtles: &amp; then it followeth that the Apoſtles goſpell was yea &amp; nay, who firſt taught &amp; practiſed one way, &amp; afterward taught &amp; commaunded to practiſe another way.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly: The Apoſtles had the bookes of the Old Teſtament in the Hebrwe tong, &amp; ſo might have vſed them before their eye in tyme of propheſying, eyther to read out of them to the Hebrues, or to tranſlate and interprett out of them to the Greecians: but they did neyther of theſe, but only propheſyed out of their harts, as the Holy Ghoſt gave them vtterance. Act. 2.4. Yea &amp; taught the primitive Churches ſo to doe: 1. Cor. 14.26. If it can be ſhewed that they did vſe the bookes of the Old Teſtament in tyme of worship to read or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprete from them, lett it be ſhewed, &amp; wee yeeld: if not thus wee hold &amp; practiſe for the preſent.</p>
                  <p>Here vppon it followeth that neyther reading the originals, nor interpreting or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating out of the originals the book being before the eye, is eyther a lawfull part or meanes of Spirituall worship.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:29151:8"/>
                  <head>Chap. 12. Of the writings of men.</head>
                  <p>Writings of men are of divers kinds: among them are tranſlations of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures a moſt principal.</p>
                  <p>To tranſlate the originals into any mother tong is aſwell, &amp; aſmuch the work of a mans witt &amp; learning, as to analyſe the Scriptures Rhetorically or Logically, to Collect doctrynes &amp; vſes Theologically, to give expoſitions &amp; interpretations of places doubtfull.</p>
                  <p>The tranſlator cannot conceave nor expreſſe in writing the whole mynd of the holy Spirit conteyned in the originals, but only ſome good part of it: the expoſitor, paraphraſt comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tator may expreſſe aſmuch as the tranſlator, yea &amp; in reſpect of ſome particulars, as Hebraiſmes, Greciſmes &amp; the like conſiderations, much more.</p>
                  <p>Ther is as good warrant to tranſlate the Scriptures as to expound analyſe, &amp; draw doctrynes &amp; vſes from the Scriptures. Marc. 5.41, Mat. 1.23. &amp; by proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from 1. Cor. 12.10. &amp; 14.13.27.39.</p>
                  <p>Ther is no better warrant to bring tranſlations of Scripture written into the church, &amp; to reade them as partes or helps of worship, then to bring in expoſitions, reſolutions, paraphraſts &amp; ſermons vppon the Scripture ſeing al theſe are equally humane in reſpect of the work, equally divine in reſpect of the matter they handle.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 13. Of reading tranſlations: &amp; of the tranſlation of the. 72. interpreters.</head>
                  <p>Hitherto apperteyneth this queſtion, whether reading a tranſlation be a lawful help or meanes in tyme of Spiritual worship or a lawful part of Spiritual worship.</p>
                  <p>If originals muſt be laid aſide as in tyme of prayer, ſo alſo in tyme of propheſying &amp; ſinging, then much more muſt tranſlations be laid aſide at that tyme: as may further be manifeſted thus.</p>
                  <p>Bicauſe the Septuagints tranſlation was a greevous ſinne for many reaſons.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For that the covenant of grace ought not to have been preached vnto the gentils til the fullnes of tyme. Mat: 10.5 6. 1. Timoth 3.16. Rom. 16.25.26 compared with, Mat. 10.5.6. &amp; 28.19. And therfor that the Septuagints by their tranſlation did communicate it to the Grecians, before the fulnes of tyme was their greevous ſinne.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Bicauſe all the Gentills ought to have been proſelytes of the Iewes Church &amp; to have come to Ieruſalem to worship<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Exod 12.43-49. Mat. 23.15. Act. 2.10. &amp; ought to have learned their tong &amp; worship, which was prevented by the Septuagints tranſlation.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Bicauſe the Hebrue characters &amp; writings were Ceremonyes &amp; ſo ought not to have been profaned among the Grecians by their writings: &amp; as the Philiſtims were juſtly plagued for the preſence of the Arke, 1. Sam. 5. So might the Lord juſtly have pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued the Grecians for that the Oracles of God were among them, &amp; fearfully abuſed by them.</p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:29151:9"/>
                  <p n="4">4. If it were vnlawful to ſing one of Davids Pſalmes in a ſtrang nation as Babylon. pſal. 137.4. then much more vnlawfull was it to tranſlate the Scriptures into a ſtraunge tong for all the Ceremoniall law was bounded within the holy land.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The tranſlation of the Septuagints out of Hebrue into Greeke, is contradictory to the Lords mercy to the Iewes church &amp; ther ſpecial Priviledges, ſee pſal. 147.19.20. Rom. 3.1.2. Act. 10.28. &amp; 22.1.-18. Eph. 2.11-15. Act. 13.46-48. contrary alſo to Rom. 16.25.26.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Bicauſe that ſeing the Hebrew writings were Ceremonyes it was vnlawful for the Septuagints to chandg them from their proper kind, &amp; to picture them out by the Greek writings for the Greeks vſe.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Bicauſe the Septuagints did of purpoſe conceale many things as judging the gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils vnworthy to know them fearing alſo leaſt they ſhould profane ſuch holy myſteries wherein their conſciences told them playnly that their tranſlation was their ſynne: alſo they did pervert many things of purpoſe, ad ſomthing &amp; infinitely corrupt their tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which was their greeve us ſinne.</p>
                  <p>Hence it followeth that ſeing the Septuagints tranſlation was ſo greevous a ſinne, therfor the Apoſtles would never account it holy ſcripture comming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy ghoſt &amp; ſo never approve the vſe of it in the Greek Churches.</p>
                  <p>Againe wee never heard of any other tranſlation before Chriſt, beſides the Septua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gints: or if ther were any, it were vnlawful by the ſame reaſons before vſed againſt the Septuagints.</p>
                  <p>Further: ther could be no vſe of the Septuagints tranſlation for reading in the Latine Church of the Romanes.</p>
                  <p>More over the new Teſtament being not written, none of it till 7.10. or 20. yeeres after Chriſts death, not all of it till Iohn had written who was the ſurviver of the Apoſtles, how could ther bee a tranſlation of the new Teſtament written during the Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les lives?</p>
                  <p>Beſides it is never mentioned that ever any Apoſtle or Apoſtolique man or Church, eyther had from the Apoſtles or vſed by their direction or approbation a tranſlation of any ſort, whathoever before the eye in tyme of Spirituall worship: if yea: let it be ſhewed.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly tranſlations therfor beganne in the Church after the Apoſtles dayes in tyme of worship, &amp; ſo were not from the beginning, in reſpect whereof they are a part of the myſtery of iniquity in worship.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 14. Of other arguments againſt reading tranſlations in tyme of worship.</head>
                  <p n="1">1. 1, Theſ. 5.21. Try all things, keep that good thing. But no man ignorant of the tongs can try whether the tranſlation be fit or good: &amp; therfor no man ignorant of the tongs can ſtrictly keep or read a tranſlation in tyme of worship.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Rom. 14.23. 1. Timoth. 1.4.-7. Heb. 11.6. whatſoever commeth not from fayth is ſinne. But no man ignorant of the tongs can of faith vſe the tranſlation ſeing he cannot examyne it whether it be good or bad, &amp; ſo beleeve or refuſe it. Therfore it is not of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29151:9"/>fayth in him &amp; ſo it is ſynne for him to vſe it before the eye in tyme of worship.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. A translation made verbatim from the originalls is abſurd by reaſon of the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the dialects: &amp; therefore vnlaw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull ſeing it edifieth not. 1. Cor. 14.26. A trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation paraphraſtical or a paraphraſt if it be lawful in time of worship to be read then why not a written ſermon.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. A paraphraſt, come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tarie or expoſition vpon a chapter which contayneth more of the contentes of the originalles &amp; the holy ghoſtes meaning is vnlawfull to be read in time of worship: therefore a tranſlation of a chapter which contayneth leſſe is vnlawful alſo to be read in time of worship.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. Levit. 22.22. Malach. 1.8.13.14. Mat. 22.37. Rom. 12.1.2. Pſal. 119.45. &amp; 103.1. God wil be ſerved with the beſt we have. But ther is no one translation the beſt we have: ſeing the Lord may in tyme of worship miniſter better to him that adminiſtreth, if hee vnderſtand the originalls if he vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtand not the originalls he hath it not at all: for it is another mans worke: &amp; therefore no one translation written may be read in tyme of worship.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. Deut. 16 16. 1. Chron 21.24. Eph 4 8. Rom. 12.3. we muſt worship God with our own not with another mans with that which coſt vs ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hing not with that which coſt vs nothing. But for one ignorant of the tongs to read the trans<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation &amp; offer it to God is to offer to God: not he mans labor not his owne: that which coſt him nothing but is another mans coſt: therfore it is vnl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ull.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Reading a translation is not commaunded nor was ever practiſed by Chriſt, the Apoſtles, or th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>imitive Chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ches in tyme of worship: &amp; ſo being deviſed by man is in the account of vayre worship. Mat. 15.9 &amp; w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll-worship. Col. 2.23. &amp; ſo a kynd of Idolatry &amp; therefore the translation it ſelfe before the eye in tyme o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worship an Idoll &amp; ſo hath a curſe denounced againſt the vſe of it in tyme o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> worship. Revel. 22.18. Exod. 20.4.5.</p>
                  <p n="8">8. A translation being the worke of a mans witt &amp; learning is aſmuch &amp; as truly an humane writing as the Apocrypha (ſo commonly called) writings are: &amp; ſeing it hath not the allowance of holy men inſpired, but is of an hidden authority: it may be juſtly called Apocryphon, for the ſignification of the word importeth ſo much &amp; therefore not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o be brought into the worship of God to be read.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. All the arguments vſed agaynſt the reading of homilies &amp; prayers may be applyed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>gaynſt the reading of translations in tyme of w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rship As:</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. They do ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt or quench the ſpirit which is contrary to. 1. Theſ. 5.19.20. 2 Cor. 3.17.</item>
                     <item>2. They are not the pure word of God &amp; ſo contrary to Eccleſ. 12.10. Mat. 15.9.</item>
                     <item>3. They are the private workes of men: contrary to. 1. Cor 12.7.8. 2 Pet. 1.20,</item>
                     <item>4. They are the private openings or interpretations of the propheſies of Scripture: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ontrary to. 2 pet 1.20.</item>
                     <item>5. They contradict the giftes beſtowed by Chriſt vppon the Church for the work of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e miniſtery: con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>trary to. Eph. 4.8.11.12. Act. 2.4. Ioh. 16.7.</item>
                     <item>6 They derogate from the vertue of Chriſts Aſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion &amp; dignitie of his Kingdome: con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ary to Eph. 4.8.</item>
                     <item>7. They blemish Chriſts bounty to &amp; care of his church. contrary to. Ioh. 14.16.18.26</item>
                     <item>8. They diſgrace the Spirit of God ſetting him to ſchoole. contrary to. 1: Ioh. 2.27.</item>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:29151:10"/>
                     <item>9. They bring into the Church a ſtraunge miniſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contrary to. 1. Cor. 12.5. &amp; ſo a new part of the goſpel or covenant con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rary to, Gal. 3.15.</item>
                     <item>10. They do not manifeſt the ſpirit which commeth from within, but manifeſteth the lettre which commeth from without. 2. Cor. 3.6.</item>
                     <item>11. Therefore they are not ſpiritual worship Ioh. 4.24. compared with. 2. Cor. 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Gal. 5.1. &amp; 4.31.</item>
                     <item>12. Children may read a translation perfectly wel: But children cannot perform a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> part of Spiritual worship: therfor reading a tranſlation is no part of Spiritual worship.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Quere: whither between the parts of Spiritual worship, that is between prayer, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying &amp; ſinging Pſalmes, a man may not inte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poſe the reading of a ſcripture or chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not intending it as worship, but as a fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ther prepara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on to worship.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 15. Objections for tranſlations anſwered.</head>
                  <p>The firſt Objection.</p>
                  <p>Rom. 4.3. What fayth the Scripture &amp; then followeth the Septuagints tranſlation Heb. 3.7. The holy ghoſt faith &amp; then follow the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>des of the Septuagints tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: &amp; it is obſerved that the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtles quote the wordes of the Septuagints tranſlation, not only wher they expound the meaning of the holy ghoſt: as Heb. 10.5. &amp; Rom. 4.3. Wher the Apoſtles follow the Septuagints not the Hebrue, but alſo in their deviſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the original: as in the ſecond Caynan Luk. 3.36.37. &amp; in the 75. perſons of Iacobs Family, Act. 7.24. where as ther is, but one caynan &amp; 70. perſon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in the Hebrue.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the firſt Objection.</p>
                  <p>If the originals themſelves are not to be vſed as helps in tyme of Spiritual worship, as hath been proved then this objection is of no force <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or tranſlations.</p>
                  <p>Secondly: if it were of force to bring tranſlations to be read in the tyme of worship <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t were avay leable thus far even to bring in to the tyme of worship the errors of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ranſlations: for ſo this objection importeth that the Apoſtles quote the Septuagints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rrors, &amp; wheras it is ſaid by ſome that in the Apoſtles intention it is no error, ſith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>riting to Theophilus &amp; the Grecians, rather then he would haza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d their fayth by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>aundging the Septuagints errors &amp; corre&amp;ing ſuch an approved Tranſlation, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ought it meet to follow that receaved deviſe of theirs contrary to the truth the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oly Ghoſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rein yeelding to mans infirmity as in the caſes of Polyga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y. &amp; Diverce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> fury in the Old Teſtament: It is thus anſwered th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t the Holy Ghoſt needeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the lyes of men, to work his work, nor the Septuagints errors to ſupport the fayth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>heophilus &amp; the Grecians: And this miſcheef followeth herevppon that rather <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ayth of Theophilus &amp; the Grecians, ſhould be endaungered the credit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es ſhould be hazarded their being found in then ſuch deviſes errors and c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>radictions. And further it is t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e thing by connivency to paſſe by ſinne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ation of Polygamy Divo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ce &amp; Vſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y: See Act. 17.30. Another thing to tranſlate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> from a tranſlation into the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> original, which is to approve them, &amp; this whoſoever
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:29151:10"/>affirmeth, ſpeaketh litle leſſe then blaſphemy.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly: therfor as Antiehriſt hath polluted all Gods ordinances ſo hath he viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the original criptures: And therfor one Caynan muſt be put out: For ſo me auncient copies have it not: &amp; for 75. Ther muſt be read ſeaventy all: Pente for Pantes: as Rom. 12.11. Kairo, Kurio, &amp; it is posſible eaſily to miſtake ſo ſmall a matter in copying out any thing as experience teacheth.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly fully to anſwer the objection whatſoever is good in the Septuagints tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was taken out of the New Teſtament, &amp; auncient Fathers of the Greek Church: For it is manifeſt by hiſtoryes that the Septuagints translation is loſt, &amp; this that goeth vnder the name of the Septuagint is a patchery made out of auncient writings: and therfor the Holy Ghoſt doth not ayme at the Septuagints Translation at all as is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported in the Objection.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Objection.</p>
                  <p>The were Greekes &amp; Grecians: Hellenes: Kai Helleniſtai. As may appeare Act. 6. 1. Rom. 1.16. The Greekes were of the Progeny of the Greekes aſwel as of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try: The Grecians were Iewes by Progeny, &amp; borne in Grecia: Therfor Paull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth himſelf an Hebrew of the Hebrewes: Philip 3: 5. Now theſe Grecians had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten their Language &amp; ſpake Greek only: And having Synagogues in the Cities where they dwelt, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d the Septuagints translation read vnto them, &amp; the Apoſtles comming into their Synagogues did approve that act of thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of reading the translation &amp; ſo it followeth that reading translations is lawfull in worship.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the ſecond Objection.</p>
                  <p>The diſtiction of Greekes &amp; Grecians is vayne as appeareth by theſe places compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together: Act. 21.39. &amp; 18.2.24. with Act. 6.1. Philip. 3.5. For Paul was borne at Tarſus in Cilicia, &amp; Aquila at Pontus, &amp; Apollos at Alexandria, And yet are all called Iewes not Helleniſts or Grecians: &amp; Act. 6.1. The Heleniſts murmured againſt the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brues, the Heleniſts did vnderſtand the Hebrue tong, &amp; had not forgotten their owne Language.</p>
                  <p>Secondly: it cannot be proved by Scriptures that the Heleniſts had the Greek trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation read vnto them in the Synagogues, it is manifeſtly otherwiſe by the reaſons vſed before againſt the translation of the Septuagints.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the worship of God properly ſo called of the whole Church of the Iewes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was performed in the Holy place at Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſalem, &amp; ſo that which was performed in the Synagogue was not properly the worship of the whole Church of the Iewes: but was of that nature that paſſed between Chriſt &amp; the Doctors in the temple: Luk. 2.46. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Act. 17.2.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly if the Heleniſts did read the Septuagints translation as a part of ther proper worship hauing forgotten their owne Language, therin were committed theſe ſynnes.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Forgetting their tong one part of the ceremonial law. Nehem. 13.24.</p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:29151:11"/>
                  <p n="2">2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>tuting worship in a common tong which was as vnlawfull as ſacrif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cing a dog</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Therefore it was a falſe worship, as it was a falſe worship to ſacrifice an vncleane beaſte vnder the law</p>
                  <p>Laſtly if they did reade the Septuagintes tranſlation &amp; the Apoſtles came in <hi>&amp;</hi> heard, it doth not follow they did allow it as a parte of the worship of the new teſtament, no more then they did allow circumciſion to be: neither did they in deede giue any allow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ance vnto it at all, ſeing they came to the ſynagogues where was the greateſt concourſe of people not to worship, but to draw them to Chriſt, not to approue their doinges but to diſproue them.</p>
                  <p>The third obiection.</p>
                  <p>Deut: 31.12. the reaſons that are alledged for readinge the law are perpetuall, and therfore the law of reading is perpetuall: the morall reaſons are, hearing, learning, fea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring god, &amp; keepinge his lawes.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the third objection.</p>
                  <p>Firſt the law of reading is not moral in the parricular act, but in the equity: for it was commaunded to be done but once in ſeaven yeare at the feaſt of tabernacles Deut. 31.10. &amp; if it had been moral in the particular act it should have been from the beginning, (which was not ſo, ſeing it beganne with Moſes,) &amp; it ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uld continue a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ter the end of the world: for moralities endure for ever: But bookes &amp; ſo reading of bookes ſhal periſh.</p>
                  <p>Secondly it is morall in the equity, that is, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> all meanes muſt be vſed to attayne the knowledg of the truth wherof reading is a principall, &amp; yet hence it followeth not that reading is eyther a part or meanes of Spiritual worship: For bookes are things meerely artificiall as are pictures &amp; ymages, Geneſ. 4.22.</p>
                  <p>Finally let it be granted that reading is morall it doth not herevppon follow that it is lawfull in tyme of Spiritual worship as a part or help thereto. Seing that reading is ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Scripture, or preparing to the worship, &amp; not worship it ſelf, &amp; ſeing that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man doth worship, he is not to prepare to worship as he doth that readeth: though I deny not but that one part of worship <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s a preparation to another.</p>
                  <p>The fourth objection.</p>
                  <p>Reading the law was performed in the Synagogue, &amp; it was not tyed to the temple or the holy place, which is an argument that reading is not ceremoniall but morall, for no part of ceremonial worship was performed from the tabernacle or Temple.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the fourth objection.</p>
                  <p>The argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t foloweth not: for although all ceremonial worship was to be performed at Ieruſalem Ioh. 4.20, Yet it is ſo to be conſtrued as intended by the woman according to the lawes direction: namely, of the worship which the Preiſts performed as ſacrificers:
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:29151:11"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> may be ſeen: D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.5-7. &amp; vſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11-19. For otherwiſe ſome ceremoniall worship; as namely circumcizion was performed any where in the land of Iſrael, for the males muſt needes be circumcized at 8. dayes old, &amp; it was imposſible to bring the males ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 100. miles within eight dayes ſpace. ſee Chap. 20.</p>
                  <p>Againe ſuppoſe reading the law to be a morall action (which yet is not ſo) hence it followeth not that reading the law is a part of Spirituall worship or a lawful help ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to in tyme therof: for by the ſame reaſon every morall duty may be made a part or meanes of Spirituall worship, which is abſurd, for that is to confound the ſecond table of the lawe, &amp; the dutyes thereof with the firſt table &amp; the dutyes thereof &amp; the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel with the law.</p>
                  <p>The fifth objection.</p>
                  <p>Luk. 4.16. Chriſt ſtood vp to read, &amp; read his text, &amp; then preached out of it: Now his actions are our inſtru&amp;ions: &amp; therfor wee are to read wordes out of a book in tyme of preaching or propheſying.</p>
                  <p>Anſwer to the fifth objection.</p>
                  <p>To this objection many things may be anſwered.</p>
                  <p>Firſt in that it was done in the Synagogue by Chriſt which was neither Preiſt not Levite, it is an argument <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> it was no proper pa t of the worship of the old teſtament, but of that nature a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> was th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>criſe performed by Chriſt &amp; the Doctors in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: ſo that reading moſt property is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ching the ſcriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es, which is not worship.</p>
                  <p>Secondly: Chriſt had the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Hebrue text of Eſay the Prophet, &amp; read or interpreted out of it, for it is doubtfull whither he vttered the Hebrue words or ſpeake the ſenſe of the Hebrue in the Syriac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> dialect: &amp; therfor from hence reading a tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot be concluded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but eyther reading or interpreting the originals.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly: Hence cannot be concluded that manner of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaching now vſed ehat a man ſhall taKe his text, &amp; then devide it into parts analyſing it Rhetorically, &amp; Logically, collecting doctrynes &amp; vſes from every member or argument or word of his text al this while he having his book before his eye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> to help him at all aſſayes: a thing wherof I am aſſured the holy Scriptures yeeldeth no warrant that it may be accounted a part of Spiritual worship: For although the Scriptures may be ſo handled, &amp; that for very profitable vſe, yet that is rather a Scholaſticall lecture, then an Eccleſiaſticall worship: it is rather an inquiſition &amp; ſearching of the holy Spirits intent and purpoſe, then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſying.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly: If wee muſt needes be tyed to this example of Chriſt (which I ſee no reaſon for ſeing reading was of the Old Teſtament) then the example of Chriſt ſhal bind alſo thus far, as that the book ſhal be layde aſide, ſo ſoone as the text is read, &amp; the book that is vſed ſhalbe the Originals: which is nothing for vocall but for mental reading, or for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting, &amp; which I never have thought to contradict, but wherin I am ready to be overruled: For this particular ſee the Quere in the Chap. 10.</p>
                  <p>See alſo the quere Chap. 14. For interpoſing the reading of the tranſlation between the parts of worship a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a further preparation &amp; help to worship ſucceeding.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:29151:12"/>
                  <p>Thus much conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ing the anſwer to Objections made for the lawfull vſe of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations in tyme of worship.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 16. Of the lawfullnes of translating the Scriptures. &amp; the vſe of translations in our account.</head>
                  <p>Although before Chriſts comming it was vnlawful to translate the Holy Originals from their ceremonial tong into any vulgar mother tong: yet the partition wall being now broken downe, translations are lawful &amp; that for theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Math. 28. Chriſt commaundeth to goe teach all nations, &amp; therfor all nations may have the Holy Scriptures translated into their owne vernacular tong, that therby they may learne the truth.</p>
                  <p>The Scriptures are a Creature or ordinance of God: &amp; therfor as it is lawful to pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture a man, a byrd a fiſh, a fowle, an angel vertue or vice, ſo is ir lawful to picture out or reſemble the Hebrue &amp; Greek original Scriptures by any vulgar translation of any tong or Language whatſoever.</p>
                  <p>Againe as God ſent the confuſion of tongs as a curſe Geneſ. 11.6.7. ſo hath he ſent the knowledg of the tongs as a bleſſing, Act. 2.6.8. &amp; bicauſe the extraordinary know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of the tong is ceaſed, the ordinary knowledg of them is left for our vſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which can never be attayned vnto, but by grammars &amp; dictionaryes whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in the Hebrue words of the old Teſtament &amp; Greek of the new Teſtament are interpreted, &amp; if it be lawfull to expreſſe in our owne tong al the Hebrue &amp; Greek words ſingly as in Grammars &amp; Dictionarves, then it is lawful ſo to doe with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al joyntly in ſyntaxe, &amp; that is a trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation whece it foloweth that translations of the holy ſcriptures are lawful &amp; neceſſary.</p>
                  <p>Further: All the members of the Church cannot poſſiblie attayne the knowledg of the tongs, which notwithſtanding they muſt endevour to their vtmoſt. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Cor. 14.1.5. &amp; ſeing the Holy Ghoſt hath commaunded al to try &amp; ſearch &amp; read: 1. Theſ. 5.21. Ioh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.39. Coloſ. 4.16, &amp; all cannot trye, ſearch, or read the originals, they muſt needes have translations &amp; other Theological writings, for their better help to the true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the original Scriptures.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly: theſe places of ſcripture compared together are ſufficient warrant for the law fulnes of translations: Mat. 1.23. Marc, 5.41. 1. Cor. 14, 27.</p>
                  <p>Now further wee have the translations of Holy Scripture in this account: viz: The translation agreable to the originals.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. Is a ſecondary Scripture, yet much inferior to the originals.</item>
                     <item>2. It may be read in the Church &amp; ſung in times.</item>
                     <item>3. It may be expounded in the Church.</item>
                     <item>4. It may be ſo vſed as a meanes to prepare vs to ſpiritual worship.</item>
                     <item>5. That the matter of the translation agreable to the originals is inſpired: but not the writing or character.</item>
                     <item>6. That it may be made the ground of our fayth.</item>
                     <item>7. That it may be made an inſtrument to trye doctryne by.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>This wee hold affirmatively: Negatively wee hold thus.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. That reading the Engliſh translatinon is no part of the ſpiritual worship of the new
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:29151:12"/>Teſtament properly ſo called: viz: o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> prayer, propheſy, ſinging of Pſalmes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. That reading the Engliſh translation is no lawful meanes or help in tyme of Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al worship.</p>
                  <p n="3">3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That the worship of the New Teſtament muſt not beginne in the book or lettre outwardly: but muſt proceed originally from the hart &amp; Spirit:</p>
                  <p>Al other publique &amp; private vſes of translations wee allow.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 17. Concerning the vſe of the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations for the hearers.</head>
                  <p>Hitherto aperteyneth another queſtion: whither the hearers may have their transla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or the originals to read or ſearch in tyme of propheſy.</p>
                  <p>The anſwer is Negative that it is not lawful for theſe reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Firſt: the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles wrote bookes, but did never devide their bookes int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> chapters or verſes: Henry Stephen firſt made the verſes of the new Teſtament: Seing therfor that chapter &amp; verſe were of mans invention, hence it followeth before chapter &amp; verſe came in the hearers could not turne to ſearch their bookes in tyme of hearing.</p>
                  <p>Secondly: the Apoſtles in quoting teſtimonyes of the Prophets doe not quote chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter &amp; verſe, but only ſay: it is written: by Zachary, by Ieremy. The Scripture ſaith: The Holy Ghoſt ſaith, &amp;c. Therby teaching vs that there is no vſe of Chapter and verſe for ſearching in tyme of hearing: For no doubt they preached as they wrote.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly: never was ther any mention made of any hearer that ever had his booke to ſearch in tyme of hearing.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly: Searching quotations hindereth attention: for the mynd &amp; affections are diſtracted from hearing by ſeeking the places: ſeing the mynd &amp; hart ſhould follow <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he voyce of the ſpeaker, as in prayer, ſo alſo in Prophefying. Nehem. 8.3.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly manuſcripts being few &amp; very deere &amp; large (ther being yet no printing found out) all could not have or bring their bookes, but there is only one kind of true &amp; profitable hearing, eyther all to have bookes and ſearch, or none to ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ve them:</p>
                  <p>Seing therfor bringing bookes &amp; ſearching them in tyme of hearing was not from the beginning: Therfor that alſo is a part of the myſtery of iniquity in hearing the word.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 18. Of the nature of eſſence of Spiritual worship &amp; the eſſentiall cauſſes &amp; kinds thereo:</head>
                  <p>Thus much concerning the helps of Spirituall wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hip: Now followeth to be conſidered the nature or eſſence thereof, which may appeare in two particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars: viz:</p>
                  <p>Firſt in the eſſentiall cauſſes of Spiritual worship.</p>
                  <p>Secondly in the proper kinds or parrs of the worship of the new Teſtament.</p>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:29151:13"/>
                  <p>The eſſentiall cauſſes of Spiritual worship are the matter and the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</p>
                  <p>The matter of Gods worship is the holy Scriptu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es which cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>neth the word o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> God, or the Goſpel, the ſubject whereof is Chriſt Ieſus:</p>
                  <p>The forme or ſoule that quickeneth it is the Spirit. Coloſ. 3.16. compared with Eph. 5.18.19.20.</p>
                  <p>This may be illuſtrated by the ceremoniall worship of the Old Teſtament &amp; the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall cauſſes thereof.</p>
                  <p>The matter of the ceremonial worship of the Old Teſtament was the beaſts, incenſe, Oyle, fatt; corne, wine, &amp; the like Creatures wherof the ſacrifices, offerings, perfumes, lampes, &amp; bread were made, with al the actions therto aperteyning.</p>
                  <p>Proportionable hereto is the matter of our ſpiritual worship Chriſt Ieſus &amp; his merits: the word of God conteyned in the Scriptures which offereth Chriſt Ieſus vnto vs: the ſeales of the covenant with all the actions therto aperteyning.</p>
                  <p>The form of the ceremonial worship of the Old Teſtament conſiſting in Sacrifices, (beſides the manner of doing) appeared in 4. things: two wherof muſt be abſent for the moſt part viz: honey &amp; leaven: two muſt alwayes be preſent: fire &amp; ſalt: Marc: 9.49. compared with Leuit. 2.11.13, &amp; 9.24. 1. Cor. 5.6 -8.</p>
                  <p>Proportionable herevnto the forme of our Spiritual worship conſiſteth in the fire of the Spirit working with the word: Act. 2.3.4. Mat. 3.11. Luk. 12.49<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 50. &amp; 24.32. 2. Tim. 2.6.7. Ierem. 23.29.</p>
                  <p>In the ſalt of ſound doctryne &amp; grace. Mat. 5.13. Coloſ. 4.6.</p>
                  <p>In the vnleavened bread of ſynce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ity &amp; truth. 1. Cor. 5.8. which was alſo ſignified by abſence of honey which hath a faculty to leaven.</p>
                  <p>As the fire came downe from heaven, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>with the ſacrifices were off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>red; Ievit. 9.24 So the holy Ghoſt like fire came downe vppon the primitive Church, to make their Spiritual ſacrifices acceptable: So muſt it doe alſo vppon ours: A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 2.3.4.</p>
                  <p>As the fire was dayly preſerved to offer withall. Levit. 6.12 13. &amp; ſtraunge fire might not be offered: Levit. 10.1. So whatſoever worship is offered vp &amp; is not kindled with the Spirit of grace in our harts is abhominable: 1. Cor. 12.7.10. 1. Pet. 2.5.</p>
                  <p>Hence it followeth that the worship that beginneth in the book or tranſlation com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth not originally from the Spirit, but from the lettre or ceremony, &amp; ſo is not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly of the new Teſtament, but of the Old: 2. Corinth. 3.6. If the tranſlation be made by one without, it commeth from a ſtraunge fire, &amp; cannot be accepted, but is ſubject to a curſe.</p>
                  <p>Thus much of the eſſential cauſſes: now follow the kinds of Spiritual worship, which are 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Praying, Propheſying, &amp; ſinging Pſalmes: Pſal. 50.14 17. 1. Cor. 11.4. &amp; 14 15-17 26. Iam. 5.13. Revel. 19.10.</p>
                  <p>Therfor praying &amp; propheſying are joyned together as parts of worship: 1. Cor. 11.4 &amp; men muſt be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ncovered at both of them.</p>
                  <p>Likewiſe praying &amp; ſinging Pſalmes are put together in the ſame ſenſe: 1. Cor. 14.15.17. Iam. 5.13. Act. 16.25:</p>
                  <p>Finally: Propheſying &amp; Pſalmes are coupled together for the ſame purpoſe, 1. Cor. 14.26.</p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:29151:13"/>
                  <p>Prayer is the showing of our requeſts to: God by the manifeſtation of the ſpirit: Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Rom. 8.26.27. 1 Cor. 14.15.</p>
                  <p>Singing Pſalmes is the shewing of our thankſgiving to God by the manifeſtation of the ſpirit. Phil. 4.6. 1. Cor. 14.15-17.</p>
                  <p>Propheſying is the publishing of the covenant of Grace by the manifeſtation of the Spirit, Act. 2.4.11.17.18. 1 Cor. 2.4. &amp; 12.7.10. Gal. 3.5. &amp; it ſerveth ſpecially &amp; prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erly for them that beleeve: 1. Cor. 14.22. Pſal. 50.16.17. &amp; it pleaſed the Holy Ghoſt to chooſe that word to ſignifie vnto vs, that as the Prophetts by inſpiration of the Holy Ghoſt propheſyed without bookes, ſo muſt wee: the difference is in this that thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration was extraordinary, ours is ordinary. Revel, 19.10.</p>
                  <p>The matter of all theſe 3. parts of Spiritual worship is one &amp; the ſame, viz: Gods word or the Scriptures, yet handled diverſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y.</p>
                  <p>In prayer Gods word or the Scriptures are delivered by way of petition in di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ection to God, requeſting things for vs optatively.</p>
                  <p>In thankſgiving Gods word or the Scriptures are delivered by way of recompenſe or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>etribution to God, indic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly or imperatively.</p>
                  <p>In Propheſying the word of God or the Scriptures are delivered demonſtratively, by way of doctryne, exhortation, conſolation, reprehenſion, &amp; by ſuch like formes.</p>
                  <p>Howſoever it be handled or delivered the matter is one &amp; the ſame the manner of delivering different: for whithor we pray, p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>opheſy or ſing, it muſt be the word or ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not out of the book, but out of the hart, 1. Cor. 12.7.11.</p>
                  <p>The demonſtration of the ſpirit &amp; powre. 1. Cor. 2.4. The manifeſtation of the ſpirit 1. Cor. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2.7. The miniſtration of the Spirit. 2. Cor. 3.8. The adminiſtring of the ſpir t. Gal. 3.5. The miniſtration of the gift. 1. Pet. 4.10. The diſpenſation of grace. 1. Pet. 4.10. Are al one in effect, &amp; are oppoſed to the miniſtery of the lettre or the Ceremoniall worship. 2. Cor. 3 6.</p>
                  <p>The miniſtration of the old Teſtament is called the miniſtery of the lettre, ſeing it diſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nced the ceremonial &amp; literal ordinances &amp; beganne in the lettre: for the Church, Miniſtery, worship, Government, Temple, Tabernacle, Cittie, Country, Meate, Drinck, Apparel, Cattel, Fruites of the ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>th, &amp;c. Were all literall &amp; ceremonial.</p>
                  <p>The miniſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation of the New Teſtament is called the miniſtery of the Spirit: ſeing it diſpenced the true &amp; ſpiritual ordinances typed by the foreſaid literal ordinances, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> in the ſpirit originally, though prepared by the lettre. 2. Cor. 3.6 - 8.24.17. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with Revel 10.10.11.</p>
                  <p>Hence it folleweth that all book worship is Iudaiſme, &amp; ſo Antichriſtian, &amp; therfore by conſequent Idolatry, now vnder the new Teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ment.</p>
                  <p>Thus much of the kinds of Spiritual worship of the new Teſtament.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 19. How the worship of the Old Teſtament did type the Spiritual worship of the new Teſtament.</head>
                  <p>The lyteral or typical worship of the Old Teſtament was performed in two places. viz: eyther in the holy place or in the court.</p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:29151:14"/>
                  <p>The Ceremoniall wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hip performed in the holy place did type moſt properly the worship of the Church of the new Teſtament which was typed by the holy place. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel. 11.1.2.2. Cor. 6.16. Heb. 8.2. &amp; 9.11. 1. Pet. 2.5.</p>
                  <p>The worship of the tabernacle or holy place conſiſted of 3. parts. 1. that which per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the braſen altar. 2. that which was performed at the golden altar. 3. that which concerned the table of ſhew bread: Exod. 37. &amp; 38. compared with Exod. 29.38. Exod. 30.7, 8 &amp; Levit. 24.1-9. Exod. 30.34-38.</p>
                  <p>At the braſen altar were offered Sacrifices propitiatory &amp; Euchariſtical. Levit, 1.3. &amp; 7.1-11 which ſignified prayer for pardon of ſyn through Chriſts ſactifice. Heb. 10.4-14 22. &amp; thankſgiving. Heb. 13.15. compared with Hoſe. 14.3. &amp; propheſying or pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishing the goſpell: Gail. 3.1. For in Preaching Chriſt is as it were ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomized.</p>
                  <p>At the golden altar was offered the ſweet perfume which ſignified prayer &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving. pſal. 141.2. Revel. 8.3.4. &amp; by proportion. Nomb. 16.46-48 Apoc. 5.8-14. &amp; prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ching the goſpel, 2. Cor. 2.14-16.</p>
                  <p>Vppo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the table of ſhewbread, was the candleſtick, &amp; twelve loaves of vnlevened bread with incenſe: vppon every one of them, which had this ſignification.</p>
                  <p>The Candleſtick with his 7. lamps burning with oile olive continually d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ning &amp; morning by Aaron &amp; his ſonnes, Levit. 24.1-9. Signified that the Church (which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> the golden Candleſtick. Apoc. 1.20. Zach. 4.) by his ſeaven lamps, that is the ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>d gifts of the Spirit, Revel. 4.5. Zach. 4.6. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt by Aaron &amp; his ſonnes, that is the doc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>yne of the Church, being kept pure, &amp; cauſed to thine bright by the Prophets of the chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> Mat. 5.14.15. nouriſhed &amp; fed continually with oile olive, that is taught dayly by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Zach. 4.14. Revel. 11.4. doth continually give light, inſtruction &amp; direction to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>er members. Pſal. 119.105. Mat. 5.16. 2. Pet. 1.19.</p>
                  <p>The ſhewbread with incenſe therevppon afterward burnt vppon the golden altar, Levit. 24.7.9. Signified that the twelve tribes that is the Church continua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſent before the Lord are accepted through Chriſts perfume, Revel. 8.3.4. are fed wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h Chriſt Ieſus the true bread of life, Ioh. 6.35. are enlightened by his word &amp; Spiritt, which are the true lamps of knowledg, Revel. 4.5.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="chapter">
                  <head>Chap. 20. Of that which was performed in the court.</head>
                  <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the holy place with the altar &amp; Preiſts did properly Signify the Church, worship, &amp; Saynts, Revel. 11.1. 1. Pet. 2.5, vnder the new Teſtament: So the cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t without the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place whither al the people came &amp; the typical ſervice performed ther, did ſignify the confuſed aſſemblies of Antichriſtian perſecuters &amp; their ceremonial worship, Revel 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2 which the Spirit in that place caleth gentils or heathen in thoſe reſpects.</p>
                  <p>The parts of typical ſervice performed in the court were reading &amp; Muſick, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ein the Levites were cheef agents, Deut. 31.9. 1. Chron. 16.4. compared with vſ. 7.37.39-42. &amp; Chap. 25.1-6-31. Nehem. 8.7-9.18. &amp; 9.3-6. Though the P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eiſis alſo &amp; any of the people might read &amp; fing, Mat. 23.2.3. Luk. 2.46. &amp; 4.16.17. Act. 13.14.15. Nehem. 8.8. Marc. 14.26.</p>
                  <p>The Scriptures read &amp; tuned Muſically were, propheſies, prayers, thankſgivings, 1.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:29151:14"/>Chron<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 25.1-6. Deut. 31.10, &amp; 2. Chron. 34.30. Pſal. 7<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. for propheſies for inſtru&amp;ion. 1. Chron. 16, 7-36. Pſal. 146.147.148.149, 150. compared with Revel. 19, 1-8, For thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>givings: Pſal. 102. the title, &amp; 92. title, for prayers.</p>
                  <p>As Muſicall Inſtruments &amp; playing vppon them was typicall, bicauſe it was Artificiall: So reading of a book was typicall alſo bicauſe it is meerely Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall,</p>
                  <p>Hence it followeth that reading propheſies was a type of propheſying, reading pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rs a type o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> praying, &amp; eading thanksgivings a type of praiſing God or thankfulnes</p>
                  <p>To conclude: as it followeth not that ſeing prayers were read in the old teſtament <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s prayers, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>or wee may read prayers now: for prayers no more doth it follow that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hough in the old teſtament they read Pſalmes &amp; propheſies, we may doe ſo now: name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y, in the tyme of worship, or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> parts, or helps of Spiritual worship, properly ſo called.</p>
                  <p>Therfor as the auncient brethren of the Seperation have taken all books from before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he eye in tyme of prayer, ſo doe wee take all bookes from the eye in tyme of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ying &amp; ſinging: &amp; that by the ſame reaſon they being al equally excellent parts of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tual worship, for God is aſmuch honoured in propheſying &amp; Pſalmes, as in praying &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ey all of them remayne in the triumphant Church in heaven: even as they were all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſed by Adam in Paradiſe before his fal: &amp; therfor are properly moral, &amp; Spiritual worship.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part of the Miniſtery of the Church.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>The firſt ſection of the Eldership or Presbytery.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 1. Of the names or titles of the Elders.</head>
                     <p>Thus much concerning the Leitourgie of the Church, now follow the offices of the Church, viz: the Presbytery &amp; Deaconry, Phil. 1.1, Eſay. 66.21. Nomb. 3.5.-10, &amp; 16: 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8. &amp; 17. Chap.</p>
                     <p>The Presbytery of the church is the company of the Elders which are for the church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the publique actions of the Church, eyther of the Kingdom or preiſthood, Heb. 13.17 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Theſ. 5.12. 1. Timoth. 4.14. &amp; 5.17.</p>
                     <p>The presbytery is vniforme conſiſting of Officers of one ſort, Eſay. 66.21. compared <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ith Exod. 28.1. &amp; with Nomb. 11.24.25. 1. Timoth. 3.1-8. Act. 14.23. philip. 1.1. Ie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>em. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.1-4. Ezech. 34.1-16.</p>
                     <p>Theſe Officers are called Elders, Overſeers, or Bishops, paſtors, Teachers, Governors, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>aders, prepoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ti, which are ſeveral names of one &amp; the ſame office conſiſting of ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>orks or qualifications</p>
                     <p>For every one of theſe officers muſt be.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. An Elder or Auncient in yeeres, 1. Timoth. 3.6. &amp; 5.1.</item>
                        <item>2. Overſee the flock, 1. pet. 5.2. Act, 20.28.</item>
                        <item>3. Feed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>ock, 1. pet. 5.2. Act. 20.28.</item>
                        <item>4. Able to teach, &amp; exhort with wholſome doctryne &amp; convince the gainſayers, 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>oth. 3.2, Tit. 1.9. Eph. 4, 11.</item>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:29151:15"/>
                        <item>5. Governe the Church. 1. Tim. 3.4.5. 1. Cor. 12.28.</item>
                        <item>6. Lead the Church in al the publique allaires thereof Heb. 13.17.</item>
                        <item>7. Are preferred to place of honor. 1. Theſ. 5.12. 1. Tim. 5.17. &amp; ſpeciall labour. 1. Timoth. 3.1.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Seing all the Elders muſt teach, exhort, convince, feed, overſee, rule &amp; lead the church therfor they may all adminiſter the ſeales of the covenant: for that is a cheef work of feeding &amp; applying the covenant &amp; that particularly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 2. Of reaſons proving the Elders to be of one ſort, viz: all Paſtors.</head>
                     <p>Firſt in the Old Teſtament ther was but one kind of Preiſts, who had al equal authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to adminiſter al the holy things: excepting the high P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eiſt, who typed forth Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus the high Pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt of our confeſſion: ſo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>tionably in the New Teſtament, ther <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s but one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ort of Elders who ſuccede the Preiſts in the diſpenſation o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> holy things. Eſay. 66.21.</p>
                     <p>As in the Old Teſtament ther was the ſanhedrim which conſiſted of 70. auncients for the adminiſtration of the Kingdom, which was a type of the vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ible church, al which E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ders in their fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt inſtitution Nomb. 11.25. did prophecy &amp; were of one kind vnder Moſes: ſo in the new Teſtament vnder Chriſt Ieſus, which is the King of the church, ther is a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n or Elder<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>p conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>ing of Auneie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s of one kind who adminiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>er <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e good of the Church, Reve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 4.4. &amp; 5.6.</p>
                     <p>Againe, If Paſtor, Teacher, Elder had been 3. Offices formally differing the Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to teach the ſeveral offices of the Church, would have mentioned them. 1. Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moth. 3. But ther he only mentioneth Biſhops &amp; Deacons according as Phil. 1.1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Biſhops are only of one ſort or kind.</p>
                     <p>Moreover, if the Apſtles had ordeyned 3. Kinds of Elders, Act. 14.23. they would h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ve mentioned them with the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eral kinds of ordination: but that i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e: for in o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e phraſe their election and ordinacion is mentioned: go their ordination being one, their office is one &amp; not three.</p>
                     <p>Further, if their had been 3. Kinds of Elders at Epheſus then the Apoſtle at Mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>um would have given them ſeveral cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dges as having ſeveral dutyes lying vppon them: but the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e Act. 20.28. giveth them one general chardg common to them all, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the duty of ſeeding the work of the Paſtor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> go<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> they are all Paſtors.</p>
                     <p>Beſides. Eph. 4.11. Paſtors &amp; teachers are all one office: for where as the Apoſtle had ſpoken diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ibutively before of Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es, Prophets, Evangeliſts as intending them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l offices, he ſpeaketh copulatively of paſtors &amp; teachers, exege<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ically teaching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> they are both one off<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ce.</p>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ſtly, if all the Elders have the paſtors gifts, &amp; the works of the paſtor, &amp; the paſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ordination, then they have all the paſtors office: But all the Elders have the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſtors gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>z: the word of wiſdome or the gift of exhortation. Tit. 1.9. &amp; therfor the paſto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> worke as Act. 20.28: 1. Pet. 5.2. which is feeding or exhorting, &amp; ſo the ſame ordination Act. 14.23. Therfor all the Elders have the ſame office of the paſtor: &amp; ſo a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> all of one ſort.</p>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:29151:15"/>
                     <p>Hence this conſectary ariſeth that the Elderſhip conſiſting of three ſorts of El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers is the invention of man, having both an Antich<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſtian Miniſtery and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in it.</p>
                     <p>And therfor when the Popiſh prelacy was ſuppreſt, &amp; the triformed preſbytery ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, one Antichriſt was put down &amp; another ſet vp in his place: or the beaſt was ſuppreſt &amp; his image advanced.</p>
                     <p>And therfor as they that ſubmit to the prelacy are ſubject to that woe of worship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the beaſt, ſo they that ſubmit to the triformed Presbytery are in like manner lyable to the woe denounced againſt then that worship the image of the beaſt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 3. Objections for three ſorts of Elders anſwered,</head>
                     <p>The firſt Objection.</p>
                     <p n="1">1, Tim. 5.17. In this place the Apoſtle maketh two ſortes of Elders viz. 1. Thoſe that Rule only: 2. Thoſe that Teach &amp; Rule. &amp; Eph. 4.11. the Apoſtle maketh two kindes of thoſe that Teach, Paſtors, &amp; Doctors. Therefore ther are three kindes of Elders formally differing each from other.</p>
                     <p>Anſwer to the firſt Objection.</p>
                     <p>The Apoſtle to Timothie teache<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h that Elders are to be honoured for two workes wel rul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng, &amp; laborious or p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul-teaching: &amp; the place doth not import a diſtribution of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fficers, but a commendacion of ſeveral workes of one office: &amp; the Specialty conſiſteth not in the works of ruling &amp; teaching which are common to all Elders: but in the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the works viz: wel-ruling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> pain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul-teaching as if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay: El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o be had in double honour for wiſe Government: but much more are they to be honoured for their laborious &amp; painful teaching: that this is ſo: ſee Tit. 1.9. &amp; 1. Theſ. 5.12.13. compared with 1. Tim. 3.1.4.</p>
                     <p>In Timo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hie the Apoſtle ſaith every Bishop muſt be Didacticos: &amp; P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oiſtamenos: &amp; therfor that ſome El<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ers are only Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cticoi, &amp; not Proiſtamenoi. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> contrary to the Apoſties intent: Further in Titus the Apoſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e expoundeth Didactico<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> to be able to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t with wholſom doctryne &amp; to convince the gainſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>es: how then ſhal ſome of the Elders be Rulers only?</p>
                     <p>Againe the Apoſtle in that place of the Epheſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ns ſpeaketh copulatively of one office, &amp; exegetically of the principal work of the paſtor which is teaching: he doth not ſay: ſome paſtors, ſome teachers, but he ſaith paſtors &amp; teachers expounding the former by the latter viz: feeding by teaching which is the principal part of feeding, &amp; for which paſtors are cheefly commended, 1. Tim. 5.17. if they labour therein painfully.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond Objection,</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Cor. 12.5.8.28. The Apoſtle ſayth. ther are diverſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tyes of Miniſteries: namely one that hath the word of wiſdom: another the word of knowledg: another that hath Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:29151:16"/>vſ, 28. Therfor the Eldership conſiſteth of 3. forts of Elders viz: of the paſtor that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ath the word of wiſdome of the teacher that hath the word of knowledg: of the Ruler that hath the quality of government.</p>
                     <p>Anſwer to the ſecond Objection.</p>
                     <p>Firſt it is graunted that ther are diverſities of Miniſteries as Eph, 4.11, 1. Tim, 3.1.8. philip, 1.1, Namely. Apoſtles, prophets, Evangeliſts, paſtors, Deacons: yet is followeth not herevppon that Elders are of divers ſorts as is pleaded, ſee vſ. 28.</p>
                     <p>Againe the word Diaconia, ſignifieth ſomtyme any Spiritual work, proceeding from any member or officer of the Church, as 2, Cor 8 4, almes is called Diaconia: 1, Pet. 4.10 Deaconein ſignifieth any work that proceedeth from any gift: So it may ſignifie heer: &amp; al the workes that folow almoſt may be referred thether: only ther are certay he Ener<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemata, mentioned vers 10.</p>
                     <p>The third Objection.</p>
                     <p>The Apoſtle Rom 12.6-8, maketh an oppoſition between prophecy &amp; an office: &amp; maketh five kinds of officers Paſtors, Teachers, Rulers, Deacons, Widowes.</p>
                     <p>Anſwer to the third Objection.</p>
                     <p>That is denyed to be the true reſolution of the place of the Romanes: for although ther be five ſeveral actions repeated, yet it doth not follow that ther are five ſeveral of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers to perform thoſe actions: For one perſon may performe then all &amp; yet be no of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, viz. teach, exhort, rule, diſtribute, shew mercy, 1 Cor 14.3.26.31, Roman 12.13 1 Cor, 5.5.</p>
                     <p>Againe the diſtributive particle Eite fowre tymes repeated, in propheſy, Diaconia, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting, &amp; teaching, importeth thus much: That the Apoſtles intention is not to ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinate teaching &amp; exhorting to Diaconia, but to oppoſe each of theſe 4. particulars to other as thus, Propheſy is the manifeſtation of a gift, 1 Cor. 14.3.</p>
                     <p>Diaconia is the office, &amp; ther are divers kinds thereof, 1 Cor. 12.5.</p>
                     <p>Teaching is one action or work of the prophets or officers, 1 Cor, 14.26</p>
                     <p>Exhorting is an other action or work of them, 1 Cor. 14 3</p>
                     <p>Hence it followeth that teaching &amp; exhorting are aſwel ſubordinate to propheſy as to Diaconia.</p>
                     <p>But ther, if Diaconia be the genus to thoſe five ſpecies following, then I ſay that Diaconia ſign fieth not an Office, but a work: And of works there are thoſe five kinds. That Diaconia doth ſomtyme ſignifie a work is playne: 1 Cor. 8.4. 1. Pet. 4.10.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly: the Apoſtle that knew how to ſpeake would never have made teaching &amp; exhortation members diſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>outive with propheſy &amp; Diaconia, If he had intended to have made them ſpecies ſubordinate to Diaconia; therefor queſtionles that is not his intention.</p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:29151:16"/>
                     <p>The Apoſtle by the commaundement of Chriſt writeth to the Angels of the ſeaven Churches of Aſia: Revel. Chap. 1, &amp; 2. &amp; 3. That is to the Paſtors which are but one in every particular Church for ſo the words are to the Aungel of the Church of Epheſus, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Anſwer to the fourth Objection.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, it can never be proved by the Scriptures that there was, but one paſtor in a Church: It is plaine, Act. 20.28. That there were many in the Church of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus (that was one of thoſe ſeaven Churches) that did performe the work of the paſtor which is p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>mainein, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eed, even all the Elders of Epheſus: Act. 20. vers 17, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with vers 28. And therfor ther were many Paſtors in the Church of Epheſus in Paulls tyme.</p>
                     <p>Againe, all Churches had Officers of one ſort, &amp; one kind of Presbytery, &amp; therefor as all the Elders of Epheſus were Paſtors, ſo were all the Elders of the ſix Churches of Aſia &amp; of all other Churches whereſoever in the world, if they had many Eld<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s.</p>
                     <p>Further, the Angel of every one of thoſe Churches doth not ſignify one paſtor only in every, Church, but eyther the College of poſtors if they were many, or the company of the moſt ſincere &amp; holy men that moſt oppoſed the corruptions of the Church, or were moſt holy &amp; zealous in life &amp; doctryne: that an angel ſignifieth a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany of men is playne Revel. 14.6.8.9. &amp; 18.4.</p>
                     <p>Laſtly, in all likely hood ther were ſome extraordinary men yet living in the churches eyther Prophets o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Evangeliſts that had extraordinary gifts, whoſe Zeale &amp; holynes might w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nne vnto then ſpecial eſtimation in the Churches: in regard whereof it might be that the Holy Ghoſt intending his Epiſtles to the whole Church, cheefly directeth them to theſe perſons ſo qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>fied as men beſt able to prevayle with the Church &amp; cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth them Aungels, whither one or more: As Iohn the Baptiſt is called an Aungell. Marc. 1.2,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 4. Of the divers gifts of Elders.</head>
                     <p>Seing al the Prophets of the Church muſt have gifts fit for edification, exhortation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> conſolation: the Paſtors of the Church muſt have gifts for the performance of the ſam workes kat, exochen, after an excellent manner &amp; in a greater meaſure.</p>
                     <p>The Paſtors excelling the prophets of the Churche in the gifts of doctryne exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, conſolation, may alſo excel one another in gifts: for al the Elders have not the ſam meaſure or degree of gifts.</p>
                     <p>In reſpect of the meaſure of gifts in the Elders, ſome excelling in one gift ſome in an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther, the Holy Ghoſt may give ſeveral titles to the Elders or paſtors.</p>
                     <p>Every Elder according as the excellency of his gift is, ſo muſt he endevour himſelf <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> edifying of the Church &amp; in the ſtirring vp the gift God hath given vnto him: 1. pet. 4. 10.11. Mat. 25.29. 2. Tim. 1.6. 1. Cor. 14.12.</p>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:29151:17"/>
                     <p>Although ſome Elder excel in one gift ſome in another, yet it followeth not that therfor they are ſeveral officers formally di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ering one from another: for not the degree meaſure or excellency of a gift or gifts, but the ſeveral kind &amp; nature of gifts &amp; works make ſeveral kinds of offices: 1. Cor. 12.4.5.6.</p>
                     <p>The Elder that excelleth in government moſt properly may be called a ruler or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, although he have the gifts &amp; powre to teach, exhort, confort, apply, &amp; that by vertue of his office. Tit. 1.9. Heb. 13.17.</p>
                     <p>That Elder that excelleth in doctryne &amp; convincing the gainſayers may moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be called a Teacher or Doctor, though by vertue of his office he may adminiſter of other paſtoral dutyes: Act. 18.28. &amp; 19.1. 1. Cor. 3.4-6. compared with Tit. 1.9. Eph. 4.11. 1. Pet. 5.2.</p>
                     <p>The Elder that exceleth in exhortation, conſolatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; application, may moſt properly be called a paſtor or ſhepheard, though by vertue of his office he is to teach convince &amp; governe. Act. 20.28. Tit. 1.9. Eph. 4.11. 1. Pet. 5:2.</p>
                     <p>As the Apoſtle doth, 2. Tim. 1.6. 1. Pet. 4.10. So may the Church give a charg to the Elder in ordination to ſtir vp, attend to, &amp; vſe his proper &amp; moſt pregnant &amp; familiar gift: which he is to mynd: &amp; accordingly to endevour himſelf in his adminiſtration &amp; thus ſhal every one as his gift is excel therein to the edification of the Church. 1. Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. 14.12.</p>
                     <p>Thus ſhal al men that have excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy of gifts when they ſhalbe added to the church be imployed in the honourable ſervice of the Church: wheras if ther be but one paſtor in a Church, men of more excellent gifts being added to the Church ſhall ſitt ſtill, leeſe ther gifts &amp; look on: which alone is an argument ſufficient to overthrow the fancy of one paſtor only in one Church.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 5. Of the works of the Presbytery or Elders in the preiſthood of the Church.</head>
                     <p>Thus much concerning the presbytery: Now follow the works of the Elders, or the presbytery. Which are of two ſorts.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Workes of the preiſthood of the Church:</item>
                        <item>2. Workes of the Kingdom of the Church.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>For the prophecy of the Church is comprehended vnder the preiſthood as a branch of it. Deut. 33.10. Revel. 1.6. with 1. Cor. 14.31. Act. 2.17.18.</p>
                     <p>The workes of the preiſthood are: propheſying, that is publishing the covenant of grace or the new Teſtament, wherto aperteyneth putting to the ſeaſes: praying ſinging pſalmes of praiſe &amp; thankſgiving vnto the Lord,</p>
                     <p>The office of the Eldership or the work of the presbytery is to lead &amp; moderate the Church in theſe Spiritual Sacrifices, in regard whereof they have their names: as Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, prepoſiti: &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>Although the presbytery lead &amp; moderate theſe Spiritual Sacrifices, yet the brethren are intereſſed in vſing their gifts for the performance of al theſe parts of Spiritual wors<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hip, 1. Cor. 14.31.26. Revel. 2.6. 1. pet. 2.5. &amp; that when the whole Church is come toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one 1. Cor. 14.23. yet things muſt be done in order, 1. Cor. 14.33.40.</p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:29151:17"/>
                     <p>Exception. The adminiſtration of the ſcales of the Covenant ſometh to apertayne only <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Elders or preſbytery, as ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap>ing did only to the preiſts: Mat. 2.6. &amp; 26.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 14.12.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 6. Of the preſbytery or Elders in the Kingdom of the Church.</head>
                     <p>The workes of the Kingdom are Admonition, Conviction, Examination, Diſputation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> communication, Abſolution, &amp; handling all matters of difference betwixt brother &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>other: &amp; if ther be any of like nature.</p>
                     <p>The Eldership is to lead &amp; moderate the Church actions &amp; ſpeaches in theſe matters &amp; cauſſes of the Kingdom &amp; government. Deut. 16.18.-20. &amp; 1.14-18. 2. Chron. 19.5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. 1. Cor. 6.1-8. 1. Theſ. 5.12.13. 1. Tim. 5.17. Heb. 13.17.</p>
                     <p>The brethren are all intereſſed in all the parts of adminiſtration though the Elders <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>d &amp; moderate them. 1. Cor. 5.4.5. 1. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> &amp; 2. Ep. 3.6. Revel. 2.2. &amp; 1.4. &amp; 1.11. &amp; 1.6.</p>
                     <p>The brethren joyntly have all powre both of the Kingdom &amp; preiſthood immedia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tely from Chriſt: Revel. 1.6. 1. Pet. 2.5. 2. Cor. 6.16-18. Mat. 18.20. &amp; that by vertue of the covenant God maketh with them, Gen 17.7. with Act 2.39. Rom. 4.11. Gal. 3.14.16</p>
                     <p>Therfor when the Church wanteth an Eldership, it hath never the leſſe powre to Preach, Pray, Sing Pſalmes, &amp; ſo by conſequent to adminiſter the ſeales of the covanant: alſo to admoniſh, convince, excommunicate, abſolve, &amp; al other actions eyther of the Kingdom or preiſthood: by neceſſary conſequent.</p>
                     <p>When the Church hath choſen &amp; ordeyned her ſelf Elders, then the Church leeſeth none of her former powre, but ſtill retayneth it entyre to herſelf to vſe when occaſion ſeweth: by neceſſary conſequent.</p>
                     <p>The presbytery hath no powre, but what the Church hath &amp; giveth vnto it: which the Church vppon juſt cauſe can take away: Coloſ 4.17. Gal. 1.9. Revel 2.2. 1. cor. 16.22</p>
                     <p>The Church hath ſome powre which the presbytery alone hath not, viz, powre of Elections &amp; communication: 1. Cor. 5.4.5. Act. 6.5. &amp; 14.23. &amp; ſo by conſequent of all other Sentences.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>The ſecond Section.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 1. Of the Treaſury of the Church, &amp; the Deacons office.</head>
                     <p>Thus much of the office &amp; workes of the preebytery:</p>
                     <p>Now follow the office &amp; workes of the Deacons.</p>
                     <p>The Deacons office reſpecteth the body &amp; bodily neceſſityes of the Saints: Act. 6.2. which is called ſerving tables in that place: as alſo bodely ſervice of the Eldership &amp; Church, Eſay 66 21 compared with Ezech 44.10-14 Nomb 3.5-10</p>
                     <p>In reſpect whereof the deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s may be termed the ſervants of the Eldership &amp; church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s the Levites were given to ſerve the preiſts &amp; the people in the tabernacle, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>b. 3.5-10</p>
                     <p>The Deacons in the new teſtament are anſwerable to the Levites in the old teſtamet: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s the Elders are anſwerable to ther preiſts: Eſay 66, 21. compared with 1. Chron 26.20</p>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:29151:18"/>
                     <p>The Deacons office eſpecially is occupyed about the treaſury of the Church. 1. chron. 16.20. compared with Act. 6.2. Ioh. 13.29.</p>
                     <p>Concerning the treaſury conſider theſe things.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Who are to contribute &amp; what is to be given to the treaſury.</item>
                        <item>2. Of what nature the treaſury is, &amp; when it is to be collected.</item>
                        <item>3. How the treaſury is to be imployed &amp; at whoſe appointment.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 2. VVho are to contribute.</head>
                     <p>They that have but two mites (as the poore widow in the goſpell) are to contribute to the treaſury, Luk 21.2. aſwel as they that are wealthy, vſ. 4. Exod. 35.20-29.</p>
                     <p>They that have much are to give much, Luk. 21.4. Act. 4.34.</p>
                     <p>They that have but litle are to contribute a litle, by proportion.</p>
                     <p>All the members of the Church are to contribute ſomthing, bicauſe the almes or con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tribution is the manifeſtation of grace, even of our bowels of mercy &amp; compaſſion, &amp; a part of our holy communion, 1. Cor. 16.2. 2. Cor. 8.2-3 7. Act. 2.42. Luk. 21.4.</p>
                     <p>As al Rivers goe into the ſea &amp; flow out of the ſea: ſo wee muſt all caſt into the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, &amp; all receave from the treaſury againe as our neceſſityes are.</p>
                     <p>Quere: whither they that are mayntayned by the treaſury are to contribute into the treaſury: as the officers &amp; poore brethren.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 3. VVhat or how much is to be given to the treaſury.</head>
                     <p>So much is to be given to the treaſury as may ſerve for ſupplying the preſent neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes of the Church, Act. 2.45. &amp; 4.34.35.</p>
                     <p>In the neceſſityes of the Church the rick muſt ſel their goods &amp; poſſeſſions for the help of the Church, Act. 2.45. &amp; 4.34.35.</p>
                     <p>In the neceſſityes of the Church the brethren muſt contribute not only according to their ability, but even beyond their ability: &amp; their extreme poverty muſt abound to their rich liberality, 2. Cor. 8.2.3. 1. Pet. 4.11.</p>
                     <p>A man is accepted of the Lord according to that which he hath, &amp; not according to that he hath not, in contributing if their be a willing mynd though only two mites be given, 2. Cor. 8.12. Luk. 21.3.</p>
                     <p>If in the neceſſityes of the Church the rich brethren do not releeve the poore by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributing to the treaſury &amp; otherwiſe, they are vnworthy members of the Church: &amp; vn natural parts of the body: &amp; are to be cenſured according to the rule: Mat. 18.15-18.1 Timoth. 5.20. Deut. 15.7-11.1. Cor. 12.22.25.26.</p>
                     <p>The rich that have frends that are needy of the Church, muſt releeve the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> themſelves, &amp; muſt not chardg the Church with them, 1. Tim. 5.4.16. vnder nephewes &amp; widowes all poore frends are to be vnderſtood by proportion.</p>
                     <p>Quere: whither: if a brother have wife &amp; children &amp; frends to releeve that are without: The Church is bound to releeve him ſo far forth as he may alſo releeve them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 4. Of what nature the treaſury is.</head>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:29151:18"/>
                     <p>The treaſury is holy. Act. 2.42. 1. Chron. 26.20, compared with Mat. 27.6. &amp; 2. Cor. 8.4 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Hence therfor follow theſe two conſectaryes.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Every holy ordinance of God muſt be ſanctified by prayer &amp; thankſgiving, 1. Tim. 4.3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. &amp; therfor Almes or contribution to the treaſury muſt be ſanctified by prayer &amp; thankſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>giving: ſee for this point, 2. Cor. 9.12-15. &amp; vſ. 8-11.1. Chron. 29.10-20.</item>
                        <item>2. Ther ought to be a ſeperation in almes &amp; contributio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the treaſury aſwel as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of our Spiritual communion, Act. 4.32. &amp; 5.13. 2. Cor. 6.17. Act. 2.42. Heb. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6. 2. Cor. 8.7. therfor they that are without if they give any thing muſt lay it a part ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>al from the treaſury &amp; it muſt be imployed to common vſe, Mat. 27.6.7.</item>
                     </list>
                     <p>The treaſury is Holy in theſe reſpects.</p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. In regard of the perſons that contribute who are Holy.</item>
                        <item>2. In reſpect of the grace manifeſted in contribution which muſt be: 1. Sympathy or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ompaſſion, 2. freenes or voluntary offering, 3 liberality or bountifullnes: Rom. 12.13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>5.16. 2. Cor. 9.5-7.</item>
                        <item>3. In regard of the perſons &amp; vſes wherto it is imployed which are the Saynts &amp; their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eceſſityes 2. Cor. 8.4. &amp; 9.12.1.</item>
                        <item>4. In regard of the Lord himſelf: it being a Sacrifice wherewith God is well pleaſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hilip. 4.18. Heb. 13.16. And a memoriall of the Saynts before the Lord. Nomb. 31. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>0.54. Phil. 4.17. &amp; a teſtimony of the love of the brethren, 2. Cor. 8.8.24. &amp; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ortable to the conſcience.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 5. VVhen the treaſury is to be collected.</head>
                     <p>The treaſury is to be collected every firſt day of the week, when the whole Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ommeth together to break bread, Act. 20.7. compared with 1. Cor. 16.2.</p>
                     <p>Reaſons hereof are divers as followeth.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Bicauſe the Lords Supper is weekly to be adminiſtred, &amp; ſo from the Treaſury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eekly ther muſt a portion be imployed to the proviſion of bread &amp; wine &amp; other ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſaryes for the more ſeemly adminiſtration thereof, Act. 20.7. compared with 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>or. 16.2.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Bicauſe the Elders are worthy of double honor, which is yeelded them by weekly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ayntenance according to their labor &amp; neceſſities 1. Tim. 5.17 - 18. Gal. 6.6.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Bicauſe the poore of the Church are weekly to be releeved, &amp; other necesſities con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ually ſupplyed Act 6.1. &amp; 2.42.</p>
                     <p>Hence it foloweth that when the greateſt communion of the church is held, the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this grace alſo of miniſtring to the necesſities of the ſaynts ſhould be exerciſed</p>
                     <p>Quere: At what tyme of the Lords day, &amp; after what manner the Treaſury is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> collected.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 6. How the Treaſury is to be employed.</head>
                     <p>The Church Treaſury is to be employed to theſe Speciall vſes.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Mayntenance of the Elders eſpecially ſuch among them as are moſt painful in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ro &amp; doctryne, 1. Tim. 5.17.18.</p>
                     <p>The Elders that are of hability ought not to require maintenance of the church, but
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:29151:19"/>ought rather to contribute to the treaſury, Act. 20.35.</p>
                     <p>The elders may ſometyme vppon good grounds work with their hands for avoyding offence &amp; helping the Church. Act. 20.34.35.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Mayntenance of the widowes &amp; by conſequent other officers that want maynte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: 1. Timoth. 5.3.4.16. Act. 6.1.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Releef of the poor brethren, alſo orphanes, &amp; widows of brethren deceaſed. Act 2.44. &amp; 4.32. 2. Cor. 8. &amp; 9. chap. &amp; that not only of the owne, but of other true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches eſpecially of them from whom they receaved the faith, Rom. 15.27.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Proviſion for neceſſary vſes: as places, veſſels, bread, wine, &amp; other implements ſo the common neceſſityes of the whole body. Exod. 35.25-29. Nomb. 7: 1. Chron. 29.1-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>Quere: whither it the chardg of bread &amp; wine be very great as it falleth out in ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> countryes &amp; ſome yeeres, &amp; the officers &amp; poore want mayntenance, the Lords ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> may not be deferred, &amp; not be adminiſtred every Lords day.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="chapter">
                     <head>Chap. 13. At whoſe diſpoſition the Treaſury is.</head>
                     <p>Seing the Deacons are the hands of the Church as it were, &amp; the ſervants of the b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the bodyly neceſſityes, therfor the delivering of the treaſury, &amp; ſo the cuſtody of perteyneth to them. 1. Chroh. 26.20.</p>
                     <p>The Eldership as they are to overſee the flock, &amp; to enquire into the occaſions &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> faires of the whole body &amp; as they are officers for the whole body &amp; in the Church name, therfor it apertey<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> vnto them for the Church to overſee the treaſury: &amp; take accouts of it. &amp; to appoint the diſpoſition of it, 2. King 22.4. Act. 11.30. &amp;. 4.35.</p>
                     <p>The Church is the owner &amp; primary poſſeſſor of the treaſury, &amp; the cheef Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> vnder: Chriſt: &amp; vnto the Church muſt the account be made finally.</p>
                     <p>Thus much concerning the Deacons office &amp; workes: &amp; concerning the treaſury <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> the Church.</p>
                     <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="demands">
            <head>Certayne demaundes, wherto wee deſire direct &amp; found anſwer, with proof from the Scriptures.</head>
            <p n="1">1. Concerning the Kingdom &amp; Preiſthood of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>VVhither the Kingdom &amp; Preiſthood of the old Teſtament were not diſtinct &amp; ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rall, both in perſon, office, &amp; actions.</p>
            <p>VVhither the Kingdom &amp; Preiſthood of the old Teſtament were not typical, ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> win<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> out the Kingdom &amp; Preiſthood of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>VVhither the Kingdom &amp; Preiſthood of Chriſt are not diſtinct, buth in office &amp; act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though vnited in one perſon?</p>
            <p>VVhither as Chriſt is both King &amp; Preiſt, ſo alſo the Saynts are not by Chriſt annoy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ted to be Kings &amp; Preiſts vnto God?</p>
            <p>VVhither the office &amp; actions of the Sayntes in the Kingdom &amp; Preiſthood, are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> diſtinct &amp; ſeveral, though vnited in perſon?</p>
            <p>VVhither the office &amp; actions of the Kingdom in the old Teſtament were not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poſition, difference, plea, &amp; ſtrife?</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:29151:19"/>
            <p>VVhither the office &amp; actions of the Kingdom of the Saynts in the new Teſtament are not of the ſame nature?</p>
            <p>VVhither the office &amp; actions of the Preiſthood of the Old Teſtament were not of vnion, concord, &amp; agreemt in Sacrificing.</p>
            <p>VVhither the office &amp; actions of the Preiſthood of the Saynts in the new Teſtament be not of the ſame nature? Rom. 15.6.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Concerning the Spirit &amp; Spirituall the Lettre, &amp; Literal.</p>
            <p>VVhither in this phraſe &amp; the like (viz. The manifeſtation of the ſpirit) the Spirit doth not ſignifie principally, both the Spiritual &amp; regenerate part of the ſoule, &amp; the Spiritual matter in the regenerate part.</p>
            <p>VVhither the manifeſtation of the Spirit doth import eyther the Spirituall matter which a man bringeth out of a book by reading: or the Spiritual &amp; gracious geſtures &amp; motions which a man expreſſeth in reading &amp; performing other actions.</p>
            <p>VVhither quenching the Spirit be not to withold &amp; reſtrayne the Spiritual matter which by the Spirit of Sanctification is ſtirred vp in the regenerate part of the ſoule.</p>
            <p>VVhither reading wordes contayned in a book doth manifeſt the Spirt; that is, expreſſe the Spirituall matter which is the regenerate part of him that readeth or rather doth not cleane put it by, leave it, &amp; diverteth to an other ſubiect &amp; ſo quencheth it.</p>
            <p>VVhither the letter doth not properly ſignifie the literall &amp; ceremonial, ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the old Teſtament, 2. Cor. 3 0. Which began outwardly ſignifiyng &amp; conveighing Spiritual matter into the regenerate part of the ſoule from without?</p>
            <p>VVhither reading the wordes contayned in a booke be not aſmuch &amp; as truly lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral beginning outwardly &amp; conveighing matter inwardly as the ſacrificing of a beaſt in the Old Teſtament?</p>
            <p>VVhither ſacrifi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing in the Old Teſtament may not as truly be accounted the manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the Spirit as reading: ſeing ſacrificing did expreſſe the Spiritual matter Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; was done with a grace by the Prei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, even as reading, doth expreſſe the Spiritual matter of the book Chriſt Ieſus, &amp; is performed with a grace by the reader?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ning, writing, &amp; Reading.</p>
            <p>VVhither lettres or characters are not invented by the witt of man to expreſſe the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulate ſounds of natural ſpeeth: &amp; whither the inventors of lettres are not mentioned in hiſtoryes?</p>
            <p>VVhither writing be not the invention of man by the ſame reaſon.</p>
            <p>VVhither reading be not the invention of man by the ſame reaſon?</p>
            <p>whither writing &amp; read ng be not things meerly artificial though ſpeaking be natural?</p>
            <p>VVhither writing &amp; reading being meer artificial deviſes may be properly called Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall worship: &amp; whither if reading be Spiritual worship, writing be not ſo alſo?</p>
            <p>VVhither that bicauſe the manu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rie trade of the butcher &amp; cook in killing roſting or boyling the Sacrifices, of the ingraver in the ſtones of the breſtplate of the Apotecary in the annoynting oyle, of the Maſon &amp; carpenter in the hewing of ſtone &amp; wood, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly of the ſcribe or paynter in writing &amp; reading, were literal &amp; ceremonial eyther worship or actions in the old Teſtament, they may now be called Spirituall worship or actions in the new Teſtament: &amp; whither one rather then another: &amp; why?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of the Holy Scriptures &amp; tranſlations.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:29151:20"/>
            <p>VVhither the holy Scriptures viz: the originals Hebrue &amp; Greek do not conteyne in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> infinite depth of truth: &amp; whither the holy Spirit did not intend by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to ſignifie al the truths, which al the men of the earth, eyther hertofore, now, or hereafter truly collect fom thence?</p>
            <p>VVhither the holy originals do not conteyne more matter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Prophets &amp; Apoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les that wrote then did conceave?</p>
            <p>VVhither the Hebrue &amp; Greek tong in their idiomes, words &amp; phraſes are not plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuly more comprehenſive &amp; ſignificative of matter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any other language whatſoever?</p>
            <p>VVhither as the original Scriptures are the jmage of the mynd of God: ſo a tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be not the jmage of the original Scriptures.</p>
            <p>VVhither the jmage can poſſibly expreſſe the thing therby ſignified, fully.</p>
            <p>VVhither it be posſible for any language verbatim without paraphraſt to expreſſe the Hebrue &amp; Greek text of the holy originals fully?</p>
            <p>VVhither a tranſlation made by the moſt learned &amp; holy men of the earth doth or can expreſſe truly &amp; fully the holy ghoſts meaning in the originals?</p>
            <p>VVhither therfor a tranſlation made by the moſt learned &amp; holy men of the earth be not an Apocrypha writing of an ordinary man?</p>
            <p>VVhither if any Apocrypha writing may be brought into the worship of God to be read all may not: &amp; whither if ſome Apocrypha writings muſt be caſt out of the church why not all, yea the translation alſo?</p>
            <p n="5">5. Of worship, &amp; vſe of bookes in tyme of worship in the new Teſtament.</p>
            <p>VVhither prayer, propheſying, &amp; ſinging Pſalmes be the true &amp; only parts of the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhip of the new Teſtament?</p>
            <p>VVhether reading be eyther prayer, propheſy, or a Pſalme?</p>
            <p>VVhither reading be lawfull in tyme of prayer, propheſy &amp; ſinging Pſalmes?</p>
            <p>VVhither reading doth not put matter into the hart of him that readeth, &amp; worship be not the producing of matter out of the hart of him that worshippeth?</p>
            <p>VVhither the Apoſtles &amp; primitive Churches did ever pray, propheſy, &amp; ſing pſalmes out of bookes, after the day of Pentecoſt. Act. 2?</p>
            <p>VVhither they did not pray, propheſy, &amp; ſing Pſalmes as the holy ghoſt gave them vtterance?</p>
            <p>VVhither the place 1. Cor. 14.26. doth not teach that a man muſt have a Pſalme, have doctryne, that is in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is hart, whence he muſt produce it by the manifeſtation of the Spirit?</p>
            <p>VVhither if 2 book muſt be laid aſide in prayer, it muſt not be ſo alſo in propheſy &amp; ſinging Pſalmes &amp; why?</p>
            <p>VVhither if a book be retayned in propheſy &amp; a pſalme, it may not be ſo alſo in prayer &amp; why?</p>
            <p>VVhither thet be two kindes of prayer, propheſy, &amp; Pſalmes, one with books, another without bookes: or one ſort of prayer without bookes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp; two ſorts of propheſying &amp; Pſalmes: with &amp; without bookes &amp; why: &amp; whither this can be warranted by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles doctryne &amp; practiſe?</p>
            <p n="6">6. Concerning a Pſalme.</p>
            <p>VVhither as in prayer &amp; propheſy one alone ſpeaketh, &amp; the reſt pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> propheſy by
<pb facs="tcp:29151:20"/>conſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 1. cor. 11.4. ſo in a Pſalme one onely muſt ſpeak, &amp; the reſt muſt coſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. 1. cor. 14.16.</p>
            <p>VVhither in a Pſalme a man muſt be tyed to meter &amp; Rithme, &amp; tune, &amp; whither vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary be not as neceſſary in tune &amp; wordes as in matter?</p>
            <p>VVhither meter, Rithme, &amp; tune, be not quenching <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Spirit?</p>
            <p>VVhither a pſalme be only thankſgiving without meter, Rethme or tune, yea or nay?</p>
            <p n="7">7. Concerning the Elders or Presbytery.</p>
            <p>VVhither al the Elders muſt not be able to teach, &amp; rule as the Apoſtle ſaith, didacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coi, &amp; proiſtamenoi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 1. Timoth. 3.</p>
            <p>VVhither didacticos that is apt to teach be not expounded by the Apoſtle, Tit. 1.9. by three particulars: viz: 1. to teach wholſome doctryne: 2. to exhort: 3. to convince the gainſayers?</p>
            <p>VVhither Teaching &amp; Ruling be not the two parts of feeding?</p>
            <p>VVhither feeding that is Teaching, Ruling, exhorting, conforting be not the paſtors office, &amp; therfor all the Elders paſtors?</p>
            <p>VVhither the Eldership hath not all their powre from the Church?</p>
            <p>VVhither the Eldership hath a negative voyce in the church that nothing can be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded without them?</p>
            <p>VVhither if moſt or the Church conſent &amp; the Elders diſſent, the matter cannot paſſe againſt the Elders diſſent?</p>
            <p>VVhither ſeing the church may depoſe &amp; excommunicate the Eldership they may not paſſe other ſentences without or contrary to their liking?</p>
            <p>VVhither may not a man propound his mater to the church without acquaynting the Elders with it in the firſt place.</p>
            <p>VVhither in the ſecond degree of admonition a man is not bound to take an Elder for witneſſe?</p>
            <p>VVhether one Elder only in a church be Gods ordinance &amp; whither if ther be choſen any Elder ther muſt be choſen more then one?</p>
            <p>VVhither the ſeales of the covenant may not be adminiſtred, ther being yet no Elders in offiice?</p>
            <p n="8">8. Concerning the Treaſury &amp; contribution.</p>
            <p>VVhither the treaſury be not Holy?</p>
            <p>VVhither contribution be not an action of the communion of the Saynts?</p>
            <p>VVhither as in other parts of communion ſo in this, ther ought not to be a ſeperati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from them that are without?</p>
            <p>VVhither the action of contribution muſt not be Sanctified by prayer &amp; thankſgiving?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <head>A Recapitulation of the Chapters to be found according to their pages.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The firſt part concerning the Leitourgie of the Church.</head>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 1.</label> Of the Kingdom of the Saynts. pag. 1.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 2.</label> Of the Preiſthood of the Saynts. pag. 1.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 3.</label> Of Spirituall worship &amp; of the Spirit. pag. 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 4.</label> Of quenching the Spirit. pag. 2.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 5.</label> Of the helps of Spiritual worship. pag. 3.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:29151:21"/>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 6.</label> Concerning bookes &amp; writing. pag. 3.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 7.</label> Of the kindes of bookes or writings. pag. 4.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 8.</label> Of the originals or holy Scriptures, &amp; of the partes of holy Scripture. pag. 4.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 9.</label> How the originals or holy Scriptures are to be vſed. pag. 5.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 10:</label> Reaſons proving the originals not to be given as helps before the eye in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. pdg. 6.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 11.</label> Objections for bookworship anſwered. pag. 7.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 12.</label> Of the writings of men. pag. 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 13.</label> Of reading tranſlations, &amp; of the tranſlation of the 72. int<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>preters. pag. 10.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 14.</label> Of other arguments againſt reading tranſlations <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> tyme of worship. pag. 11.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 15.</label> Objections for tranſlations anſwered. pag. 13.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 16.</label> Of the lawfulnes of tranſlating the Scriptures, &amp; the vſe of tranſlations in our account. pag. 17.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 17.</label> Concerning the vſe of the tranſlation for the hearers. pag. 18.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 18.</label> Of the nature or eſſence of Spiritual worship &amp; the eſſential cauſſes &amp; kindes thereof. pag. 18.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 19.</label> How the worship of the old Teſtament did type the Spiritual worship of the new Teſtament pag. 30.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 20.</label> Of that which was performed in the court. pag. 21.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond part of the Miniſtery of the Church. pag. 22.</head>
               <list>
                  <head>The firſt ſection of the Eldership or Presbytery. pag. 22.</head>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 1.</label> Of the names or titles of the Elders. pag. 22.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 2.</label> Of reaſons proving the Elders to be of one ſort viz: all Paſtors. pag. 23.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 3.</label> Objections for three ſorts of Elders anſwered. pag. 24.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 4.</label> Of the divers gifts of Elders. pag. 26.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 5.</label> Of the works of the Presbytery or Elders in the Preiſthood of the church. pa. 27</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 6.</label> Of the workes of the Presbytery or Elders in the Kingdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the church. pag. 28.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>The ſecond ſection.</head>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 1.</label> Of the treaſury of the Church &amp; the Deacons office, pag. 28.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 2.</label> Who are to contribute. pag. 29.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 3.</label> What or how much is to be given to the treaſury. pag. 29.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 4.</label> Of what nature the treaſury is. pag. 29.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 5.</label> When the treaſury is to be collected. pag. 30.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 6.</label> How the treaſury is to be employed. pag. 30.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>Chap. 7.</label> At whoſe diſpoſition the treaſury is. pag. 31.</item>
                  <item>Certayne demaundes, pag. 31.</item>
               </list>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:29151:21"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
